<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The young man's guide in his journey to heaven, or, Travelling spiritualized</title>
            <author>S. T., 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T60</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24165</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07985271</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07985271</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40745</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64275)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40745)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1214:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The young man's guide in his journey to heaven, or, Travelling spiritualized</title>
                  <author>S. T., 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Parkhurst,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: S.T.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life.</term>
               <term>Salvation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40745:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40745:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Young Man's GUIDE IN HIS JOURNEY TO HEAVEN OR <hi>Travelling Spiritualized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chapel,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:40745:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40745:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO Young Men.</head>
            <p>MAns Life's a Journey, from his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Womb he ſets out; this World's the Country through which he is Travelling: He begins with Crying, as if he foreſaw how difficult and dangerous his Way would be. The Stages, from Infancy to Childhood, from Childhood to Youth; from Youth to Manhood, which ſoon declines and old Age ſucceeds, in which he will ſay, <hi>I have no Pleaſure in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Youth need a Guide, here is one offered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem at a Cheap Rate, 'tis not neceſſary his Name be known, ſo that he be skilful and faithful, no more than the Authors of thoſe two Excellent Books, <hi>The Whole Duty of Man,</hi> and <hi>Divine Breathings.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40745:3"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Young Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Read, Conſider and Practice the Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and you will not repent your Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, 'tis not unlikely but Parents and Friends of Young Perſons may make Preſents of them, to thoſe who are beginning their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel through this lower World. That it may Anſwer its End in Conducting many to the upper and better World of Reſt and Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is the deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. T.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April 8th. 1700.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:40745:3"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. A <hi>Wiſe Traveller deſigns to go to ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Place, and propoſeth ſome certain End for his going thither.</hi> Page 1.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>A Wiſe Traveller caſts up the coſts of his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney before he undertakes it.</hi> p. 3.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>A Wiſe Traveller makes diligent Enquiry which is the right Way, and is very careful to follow Directions.</hi> p. 6.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>A Wiſe Traveller ſets out Early in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he may not be benighted before he comes to his Journeys end.</hi> p. 10.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>A Traveller who hath Loitered, or deferred ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out in the Forenoon, muſt double his Pace in the Afternoon.</hi> p. 15.</item>
               <item>6. <hi>A Traveller is many Times put out of his Way by falſe Directions.</hi> p. 19.</item>
               <item>7. <hi>A careful Traveller is much grieved, when he finds himſelf to be out of his Way, and haſts to get into it again, and is never quiet till he hath recovered it.</hi> p. 30.</item>
               <item>8. <hi>A Traveller having been once out of his Way, will be more wary and careful ever after to keep in it.</hi> p. 36.</item>
               <item>9. <hi>Every Traveller is deſirous to have as much Company with him in his Jonrney as he can, eſpecially of his Relations and Friends.</hi> p. 40.</item>
               <item>10. <hi>A Traveller will keep Company with ſuch and ſuch only as are going the ſame way that he is, and to the ſame Place.</hi> p. 48.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:40745:4"/>
               <item> 11. <hi>He that Travels in a ſtrange Countrey, muſt look to meet with many Affronts and Injuries with many Afflictions and Hardſhips.</hi> p. 59.</item>
               <item>12. <hi>He that Travels about Buſineſs, which highly concerns him, reſolves to go through all Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and Diſcouragements.</hi> p. 64.</item>
               <item>13. <hi>He that makes haſte in his Journey by Galloping or Running, will cauſe all the Dogs in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to follow him by Barking.</hi> p. 70.</item>
               <item>14. <hi>He that undertakes a long Journey through dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult Paſſages, had need be a ſtrong Man and well provided for his Journey.</hi> p. 74.</item>
               <item>15. <hi>It is very miſchievous when Travellers fall out and quarrel by the Way, it makes their Journey very uncomfortable.</hi> p. 79.</item>
               <item>16. <hi>A Traveller who carries Treaſure with him, and ſuſpects that he may meet with Thieves will go well armed.</hi> p. 94.</item>
               <item>17. <hi>He that Travels with a ſtrong Guard, need not fear to be robb'd, or hindred in his Way.</hi> p. 100.</item>
               <item>18. <hi>Though the Traveller find good Entertainment in his Inn, yet he takes not up his abode there, but is reſtleſs till he come to his own Home.</hi> p. 107.</item>
               <item>19. <hi>Many a Traveller is ready to faint in his Way, and to fear that he ſhall never reach his Journeys end, which yet doth attain it with Safety.</hi> p. 111.</item>
               <item>20. <hi>When a Traveller after a long and dangerous Journey is return'd in Safety to his Fathers Houſe: How will his Father embrace him? How will all his Relations welcome him? What mutual Joy and Rejoycing will there be.</hi> p. 115.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:40745:4"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>Tho. Park<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <list>
               <item>MR. <hi>Clarkſon</hi>'s Practical Diſcourſes in <hi>Folio. Watſon</hi>'s Body of Divinity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quick</hi>'s Synodicon.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Catholick Theology.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Books written by the Reverend J. Flavel.</head>
               <item>THE Fountain of Life opened, or a Diſplay of Chriſt in his Eſſential and Mediatorial Glory. Containing Forty two Sermons on va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Texts.</item>
               <item>The Method of Grace, in bringing home the Eternal Redemption, contriv'd by the Father, and accompliſh'd by the Son, through the Effectual Application of the Spirit unto God's Elect. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Second Part of the Fountain of Life.</item>
               <item>A Treatiſe of the Soul of Man, wherein the Divine Original, Excellent and Immortal Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Soul are opened, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Divine Conduct, or Myſtery of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Navigation Spiritualiz'd: Or, A new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs for Sea-Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Saint indeed: The great Work of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</item>
               <item>A Touchſtone of Sincerity: Or, Signs of Grace, and Symptoms of Hypocriſie: Being the Second Part of the Saint indeed.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:40745:5"/>
               <item> A Token for Mourners: Or, Boundaries for Sorrow for the Death of Friends.</item>
               <item>Husbandry Spiritualiz'd: Or, the Heavenly Uſe of Earthly Things.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Philip Henry</hi>'s Life.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Reynold</hi>'s Miniſter of <hi>Notingham</hi> his Life.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Mead</hi>'s Almoſt Chriſtian.</item>
               <item>—Early Obedience.</item>
               <item>—<hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Wheels.</item>
               <item>—Spirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Wiſdom improv'd againſt Temptations.</item>
               <item>—A Sermon of Union.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Joſeph Barrett</hi>'s Funeral Sermon, to which is annexed his Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maſon</hi>'s Spiritual Songs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barton</hi>'s Hymns in Six Centuries.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Allen</hi>'s Alarum.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Allen</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Guide.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Adam</hi>'s Funeral Sermon.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe concerning the Redeemers Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over the Inviſible Worlds; ſome Part whereof was Preach'd on the Occaſion of the Death of <hi>John Houghton</hi> Eſquire.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Bate</hi>'s Funeral Sermon.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Mead</hi>'s Funeral Sermon.</item>
               <item>All Four by the Reverend Mr. <hi>John Howe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Shortneſs of Time. By <hi>F. Fuller.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Bradford</hi>'s Eight Sermons Pleach'd at St. <hi>Paula,</hi> at the Lecture founded by the Honourable <hi>Robert Boyle</hi> Eſquire.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40745:5"/>
            <head>THE YOUNG Man's Guide, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I. <hi>A Wiſe Traveller deſigns to go to ſome certain Place, and propoſeth ſome certain End for his going thither.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THERE are but two Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to which all Men in the World are going, Heaven and Hell. Now the greateſt Part of Men never ſeriouſly conſider to which of theſe the courſe of their Life leads them, it is ſaid of <hi>Abraham, He went out not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whither he went;</hi> but it may be ſaid <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 8.</note> of moſt, that for want of Faith, they go on not knowing whither they are going. Fools and Mad Men are always Rambling, but can give no account whither, and therefore many Times run upon Death and Danger; ſuch Mad Men, and worſe, are all prophane Men,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40745:6"/> who never conſider whither they are going till they drop into Hell, but now the ſerious Godly Chriſtian in the whole courſe of his Life deſigns for Heaven ſets his Face <hi>Sion-</hi>ward, is bound for the <note place="margin">Jer. 5. 5.</note> New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſeeks for a better Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, is journeying through the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 16.</note> of this World to the Heavenly <hi>Canaan;</hi> every Journey he takes on Earth, promotes his Journey to Heaen. Every Thought, Word and Action, he ſincerely deſires may be ſo many ſteps in Heavens way. He aims at Heaven, his Eye is there, his Heart is there, and he is reſtleſs till he be there, where he knows he ſhall enjoy Eternal Reſt where he ſhall be freed from all Satan Temptations, from all his Luſts and Corruptions, from all his Doubts and Fears, from all his Sorrows and Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, from all Mens Hatred and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4. 17. 1 John 3. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>where he ſhall be for ever wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Lord; ſee him as he is,</hi> and ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him as he deſires; where he ſhall behol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Bleſſed Saviour, who was Crucifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for him, Crowned with Glory and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jeſty; where he ſhall with innumera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Saints and Angels, ſing Praiſes and H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lelujahs, to him that ſits upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Throne, and to the Lamb for ever mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40745:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>A Wiſe Traveller caſts up the Coſts of his Journey, before he <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SO every true Chriſtian who ſeriouſly reſolves for Heaven, when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins his Spiritual Race, and ſets forth in that way which is called Holy, ought wiſely to conſider what it will coſt him to be Religious, and what difficulty he muſt expect to meet with in the way to Heaven. Our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour, who is Wiſdom it ſelf, hath taught this Leſſon of Heavenly Wiſdom to all who will be his Diſciples and follow him, <note place="margin">Luke 14. 26.</note> that they muſt make their account be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Hand, leaſt with ſhame they revolt from him afterward; and when they meet with hardſhip in the way to <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> ſhould meditate their return to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt:</hi> Every one therefore that minds to be a Chriſtian indeed, and perſevere a Chriſtian to the end, muſt and will ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider before-hand, <hi>that through</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 14. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>much Tribulation, he muſt enter into the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40745:7"/> Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> That he muſt <hi>give all Diligence to make his Calling and Election</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 10. Luke 13. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>ſure.</hi> That he muſt <hi>ſtrive to enter in at the ſtraight Gate</hi> of Heaven; yea, he muſt ſtrive as one that is in an Agony, as the Word ſignifies: He knows that he muſt <hi>Meditate in the Law of God Day</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm 1. 2. 1 Theſſ. 5. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>and Night:</hi> That he muſt <hi>Pray without ceaſing,</hi> that his Prayers muſt be Wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and put up with ſtrong Cries and Tears. That he muſt <hi>ſet a Watch before</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 141. 3. Pro. 4. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>the Door of his Lips,</hi> and <hi>keep his Heart with all Diligence;</hi> and make a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with his Eyes, that he muſt walk exactly every ſtep of his Way, <hi>and be</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Holy in all manner of Converſation;</hi> yea, he reckons that he muſt paſs through harder Duties yet, and ſuch as are more contrary and thwarting to Fleſh and Blood; and to which Carnal Reaſon will cry out, <hi>Theſe be hard ſayings, who</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>can bear them?</hi> He knows that ſelf muſt be Denied, the World muſt be Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, Luſt and Corruption muſt be Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, though they be as dear as Right Hands and Right Eyes. He knows that <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 29. Mat. 10. 38.</note> the Yoke of Chriſt muſt be taken on, and the Croſs of Chriſt muſt be taken up; He knows that he ſhall be hated of all Men for Chriſt's ſake; yet he muſt <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 29.</note>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40745:7"/> Love them, while they Hate him, <hi>Bleſs them</hi> while they <hi>Curſe him, Pray for them</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 24.</note> while they <hi>deſpitefully uſe him, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute him.</hi> He knows it may come to that, that he muſt part with his deareſt Friends and neareſt Relations, with his Goods and Good-Name, with his Eſtate and Liberty, nay with his Life too, <note place="margin">Luke 14. 26.</note> if he will not be falſe to Chriſt and his own Conſcience: And laſtly, He knows that this is the Way, that all that have gone to Heaven before him have gone thither in; He knows that all the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God have been great Sufferers, and that the Son of God was the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Sufferer of all: This and much more he hath deliberately conſidered with himſelf, and heartily agrees to the Terms and Conditions, and thinks them all Holy, Juſt, and Good; and ſo he goes on from Strength to Strength till he appears before God in the Heavenly <hi>Zion;</hi> and like another <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leb</hi> not being frighted with the difficulty of Duties, or the Danger of Sufferings, he marcheth on with an holy Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and with a ſtrong Confidence in Gods aſſiſtance (of encouraging others ſo to do) till he triumphantly arrive at the Heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:40745:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>A Wiſe Traveller makes diligent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, which is the</hi> right Way, <hi>and is very careful to follow Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere be many that make the Way to Heaven ſo broad that none can miſs it, as if they knew the Way thither better than Chriſt himſelf, who ſaith <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 14.</note> that <hi>ſtraight is the Gate, and narrow is the way that leads to Life, and few there be that find it;</hi> but all thoſe who are Followers of Chriſt do find by Experience that his Words are true, <hi>Ardua eſt ad Regnum Via,</hi> the Way to his Kingdom is no ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie Way; and therefore they are full of Doubts and Fears, leaſt they ſhould miſs it, and are very ſollicitous a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive to be directed and ſet in the right Way, <hi>They ask the Way to</hi> Zio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 50. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>with their Faces thitherward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> They run to the faithful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt (who are as Leaders and Guides, who are as Lights upon a Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> to ſhew Men their Way to Heaven
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40745:8"/> and cry out to them as thoſe, <hi>Men and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Brethren, What ſhall we do?</hi> And with the <hi>Jaylor, Sirs, What muſt I do to be</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 16.</note> 
                  <hi>ſaved?</hi> And with the Young Man, <hi>What ſhall I do, that I may have Eternal</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Life?</hi> They beg of theſe <hi>Samuels</hi> to teach them the good and the right Way, and of theſe Servants of the moſt High God, to ſhew them the Way of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> They reſort to experienced Chriſtians, who have been longer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Ways of God, and earneſtly importune them to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their Experiences; they enquire of them, How they may avoid or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuch a Temptation; How they may mortifie ſuch a Corruption? How perform ſuch a Duty? How bear ſuch an Affliction? And how undergo ſuch Sufferings? and many other ſuch Caſes they deſire to be reſolved in: As they ſay of Children, they will be always asking of Queſtions, ſo it may be ſaid of the Children of God, they will not only go to the Miniſters and Servants of God for Direction: But,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They will go to the Great God himſelf, and will beg of him, as <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>Cauſe me to know the Way</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 143. 8.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:40745:9"/> 
                  <hi>wherein I ſhould walk, for I lift up my Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to thee. Teach me O Lord the Way of thy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Statutes, and I ſhall keep it unto the end ſhew me thy Way, O Lord; teach me thy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 25. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Paths;</hi> and becauſe he knows that God hath fully and plainly revealed his Wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and his Way in his Word: Therefore,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> As the Traveller goes to his <hi>Map-Book</hi> for Direction, ſo doth he to <hi>the Book of God,</hi> there he finds eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtep of his Way chalked out before him. All the <hi>credenda, agenda,</hi> and <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gienda,</hi> what he muſt <hi>believe,</hi> what he muſt <hi>do,</hi> and what he muſt <hi>leave undone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> there he finds Direction, how he muſt walk in every Condition, in every Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, in every Age, in every Calling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in every Holy Duty: There he finds that he muſt be Regenerate and Born again, or <hi>he cannot ſee the Kingdom of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">John 3. 3. Mark 16. 16. 2 Theſſ. 1. 8. Tit. 2. 11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>God;</hi> he muſt <hi>Repent,</hi> and <hi>Believe,</hi> and <hi>obey the Goſpel,</hi> or he cannot <hi>be ſaved<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> he muſt <hi>live ſoberly, righteouſly, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in this preſent World,</hi> if he will live happily in the World to come. Many ſuch Directions as theſe, he finds in tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Bleſſed Book, which will <hi>be a Lamp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 105.</note> 
                  <hi>his Feet, and a Light to his Paths:</hi> Now as a careful Traveller takes notice o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> every Place he is to paſs through, and
<pb facs="tcp:40745:9"/> punctually obſerves them, cannot fail to get ſafe to Heaven. But it is as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a Man to carry a Ship to the <hi>Indies</hi> without a Card or Compaſs, as for a Soul to go to Heaven, without fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Directions of Gods Word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> As the wary Traveller, who would be ſure to keep the right Way, will take his Guide along with him; ſo will a Child of God, deſire to have the Spirit of God for his Guide to Heaven, that when he is turning to the Right Hand or to the Left, he may hear that Voice behind him ſaying, <hi>This is the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 30. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Way walk in it,</hi> he will pray that the good Spirit of God, <hi>will lead him into the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 143. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Land of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs:</hi> That the Spirit of Truth, <hi>may lead him into all Truth:</hi> We read that thoſe who are in Chriſt, <note place="margin">John 16. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>do walk after the Spirit,</hi> ſo that the Spirit goes before them, and leads them in the way. It is ſaid, <hi>As many as are led by</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 1, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>the Spirit of God, they are the Sons of God,</hi> which is convertible. And it may as truly be ſaid, <hi>As many as are the Sons of God, they are led by the Spirit of God.</hi> Now he that hath ſuch an unerring Rule, as the Word of God to direct him in his Way; and ſuch an infallible Guide, as the Spirit of God to lead him
<pb facs="tcp:40745:10"/> in his Way, he cannot but get ſafe to his Journeys end, and that is to Heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>A</hi> Wiſe <hi>Traveller ſets out Early in the Morning, that he may not be Be-Nighted, before he comes to his Journeys End.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CHriſtian, if thou reſolveſt for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, learn this Point of Heavenly Wiſdom. Begin thy Journey betimes, ſet out in the Ways of God in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thy Age; leaſt the Night of Death ſurprize thee before thou haſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed thy Courſe, and ſo all thy Hopes periſh. Delaies are dangerous, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in matters of Spiritual and Everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Concernment. How many Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are now in Hell, that thought to Repent before they Died, but Died be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they Repented? With how many hath their Sun ſet at Noon? With how many in the Morning of their Days? With how many hath Sun-riſing and Sun-ſetting come together? O what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40745:10"/> Madneſs is it then to defer thy Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance till hereafter! Anſwer me two Queſtions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. Haſt thou the Command of Time? Surely no! the Time preſent on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is thy Day, not one Minute of what is future may be called thine; thou maiſt <note place="margin">Iſa. 4. 14.</note> as ſoon recal all the Years that are paſt, as Promiſe thy ſelf one Year or one Hour to come: <hi>Thou Fool, this Night</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luke 12. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>thy Soul may be required of thee:</hi> However thy maiſt hear a Voice, <hi>Give an account of thy Stewardſhip, for thou maiſt be no</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> 
                  <hi>longer Steward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2. If thou hadſt Hereafter in thy own Hand, and could Promiſe thy ſelf longer Life, haſt thou Repentance in thine own Hand? Surely no! For Repentance is the Gift of God, and how canſt thou preſume he will beſtow it upon thee, who haſt ſo often refuſed it when it was offered? Canſt thou think that when thou haſt given up thy Youth and Strength to Satan and thy Luſts, that the Bleſſed and Holy God will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Satans leavings. Thou wouldſt judge that Perſon to be light-Headed, or out of his Wits, that ſhould talk of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning a long Journey on Earth, when he is going out of the World. Surely
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40745:11"/> he is worſe then Mad, that defers ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out in his Journey to Heaven, till Old-age, Sickneſs, or a Death-bed; thou wilt have enough to do, when thou art Old to conflict with the Infirmities of Age, when thou art Sick to conflict with thy Pains, when thou art Dying to conflict with the King of Terrours, and with Satan, who will be ſure to aſſault thee with his ſtrongeſt Temptations; and he that tells thee now it is too ſoon, will then tell thee it is too late. An old Convert is a great Rarity; <hi>Can a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 13. 23.</note> Blackamore <hi>change his Skin, or a Leopard his Spots,</hi> much leſs <hi>can he that is accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do Evil, learn to do Good;</hi> by which Word of God we learn, <hi>That a Young Sinner is more like to make an old Devil, than a Young Saint:</hi> The contrary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>A Young Saint an Old Devil,</hi> is a Leſſon which the Old Devil teacheth Younger Sinners, that he may deceive them, and rob them of their Souls. But the God of Truth, teacheth us another Proverb.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Young Saint will be an Old Saint<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Train up a Child in the Way wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 22. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhould go, and when he is Old he will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> depart from it. Timothy had learned the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Scriptures from a Child,</hi> He walked ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40745:11"/> to that Rule all his Life. <hi>John</hi> was a Young Saint, and an Old Saint. It is the Obſervation of one, that he that was the Beloved Diſciple, and lay in Chriſt's Boſom was the youngeſt of all; Chriſt loveth young Diſciples, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way then with all delaies and imitate good <hi>Joſiah,</hi> who while he was yet young began to ſeek after God: What art thou afraid of being Happy to ſoon? Surely thou art ſo, if thou art afraid of being Holy too ſoon; for Holineſs is the only way to Happineſs. Art thou un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 14.</note> to part with thy Luſts and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Pleaſures too ſoon? that is, as if thou ſhouldſt ſay, I am nnder the moſt vile and cruel Slavery and Bondage in the World, yet I am unwilling to be ſet at Liberty too ſoon. I am deadly Sick of the Leproſie, or of the Plague, yet I would not be cured too ſoon. Certainly <hi>Egyptian</hi> or <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage is Freedom, compared with the Bondage of Sin and Satan: The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie of the Skin is cleanneſs and ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, if you compare it with the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie of the Soul; The Plague of the Body is Health and Eaſe, in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the Plague of the Heart. Well then, be perſwaded to ſet out for <note place="margin">Eccl. 12. 1.</note>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:40745:12"/> Heaven, in the Morning of thy Days, ſacrifice the firſt Fruits of thy Time to God, <hi>Remember thy Creator in the Days of thy Youth.</hi> Say not with <hi>Auſtin</hi> before his Converſion, <hi>Da Domine Poenitentiam ſed non ad huc;</hi> Lord give me Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but not yet. But rather cry out, as he did after Converſion; <hi>Lord, why not now, why not now? Plutarch</hi> reports of one who in the midſt of his Feaſting and Jollity, received a Letter which gave him notice, that his Life was in preſent Danger; he put up the Letter in his Pocket, ſaying, <hi>Seria Cras,</hi> I will think of ſerious Matters to Morrow, do not thou ſay after him, leaſt it coſt thee the Life of thy Soul, as it did him the Life of his Body, for he was poyſon'd at that Dinner; but do thou labour to ſay, as another once did: <hi>Cur avi in Juventut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ut benè viverem, in Senectute ut benè mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riar.</hi> I took care in my Youth to liv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> well, and in Old-age to die well. And learn this Leſſon of the Wiſe Traveller He that ſets out moſt Early, will fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Journey moſt Eaſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40745:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>He that hath Loitered or Deferred ſetting out his Journey in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, muſt double his Pace in the Afternoon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have endeavoured in the Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the foregoing Obſervation, to give thee ſerious Advice, to ſet out in thy Journey towards Heaven in the Morning of thine Age; and certainly this would make thy Journey, much more eaſie and comfortable, and would free thee from many Fears and Doubts, and prevent much Sorrow and Grief of Heart; but if this Counſel come too late, and thou haſt loitered and defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to begin thy Journey in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon of thy Day, then learn this Leſſon of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arthly Traveller, to make all the ſpeed thou canſt in the Afternoon, ſince thou haſt ſet out late, make the more haſte now thou art on thy Way. Run like <hi>Ahimaaz,</hi> who though he did ſet out after <hi>Cuſhi,</hi> yet over-ran him <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18. 23.</note> and got before him; labour to overtake
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40745:13"/> thoſe who were in Chriſt before thee, give double <hi>Diligence to make thy Calling</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>and Election ſure,</hi> labour to redeem the Time, and to <hi>abound in the Work of the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 58. Phil. 2. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord,</hi> to make thy Religion thy buſineſs, and <hi>to Work out thy own Salvation with Fear and Trembling.</hi> And what Advice I give to thee herein, I deſire to give it to my own Soul. For I muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (and I deſire to do it with ſhame and ſorrow) that in the Days of my Youth, I walked after the Faſhion of this World, and after the Luſts of mine own Heart, and have even wearied my ſelf in ways of Wickedneſs; but as for the pleaſant Ways and peaceful Paths of God, my corrupt Heart accounted them too ſtrict, and did wholly decline them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Oh that my Head were Water, and mine Eyes a Fountain of Tears, that I might weep Day and Night,</hi> for my great Folly and Madneſs: How can I ſufficiently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail it (if it were with Tears of Blood) that I ſhould ſo miſerably miſpend the Prime of mine Age, and put my ſelf ſo much behind-Hand in my Journey to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Everlaſting Happineſs; that while my Underſtanding, Memory, Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all the Faculties of my Soul were lively and vigorous, and fit for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40745:13"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Service of my God, I ſhould ſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivers Luſts and Pleaſures; and that while I enjoyed Youth and Health, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trength, I ſhould not take one ſtep in Heavens-way: How did Pride, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſion, and Wantonneſs, and Volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uouſneſs, devour my precious Time and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Heart too! How often have I ſpent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he whole Day in Hunting or Bowling, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd a great part of the Night in Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing and Carding? ſure this was not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay to Heaven. Oh the Infinite Mercy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Patience of my God, that had not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen cut me off, and made me to reap <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Fruit of mine own Ways! But O my Soul, how canſt thou ſufficiently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the free Grace and infinite Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs of my Bleſſed God! who ſtopped <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hee in thy Carrear towards Hell, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urned thy Feet into the Way of Peace! Conſider now what thou haſt to do, <hi>Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, and all that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 103. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>within me, bleſs his Holy Name:</hi> Who hath opened thy Eyes at laſt, and hath given thee an Heart to forſake the Ways of Death, and to chuſe the Way of Life. Be heartily humbled, and bewail, that thou hadſt not ſet out ſooner, in ſo Good, ſo Sweet, and ſo Holy a way; and that thou didſt ſo linger in <hi>Sodom,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:40745:14"/> and wer't Content to abide ſo long a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it were in the Suburbs of Hell, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> now thou art in the Right Way wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on chearfully in it; lift up thy feebl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Knees, and make ſtraight Paths: Thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou canſt never do enough for tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, who hath done ſo much for Thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſince he hath ſet thy Heart at Liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty, do thou run the Ways of his Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandments; ſince thou haſt done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much againſt him in the former pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of thy Life, labour to do the more fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him in the remaining Part; that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> though thou didſt ſet out late, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> maiſt with Safety and Comfort arrive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy Journeys end. For ſhame, do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou whoſe Feet were as Hinds Feet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Way of Sin, creep on a Snails pac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Ways of God. Now Chriſtia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (who readeſt theſe Lines) if thou ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obtained that ſpecial Grace and Favou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be Converted, and brought into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Right Way in the Days of thy Yout<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> O Live in Admiration of the Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Grace of God, and ſhew thy thankfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>neſs by walking chearfully in his Way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But thou art in my Condition, if tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haſt neglected to ſeek the Kingdom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God in the firſt Place, and to walk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the way of Holineſs, which leads <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:40745:14"/> that Kingdom (as I have done.) Let us now ſet to it with our whole Heart. <hi>Let us now forſake our wicked Ways, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>unrighteous Thoughts, and let us return to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Lord, and he will have Mercy upon us, and to our God and he will abundantly Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</hi> Let us, who have brought forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one but bitter Fruits in our Youth bring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orth the Fruit unto Holineſs in our Old-Age, and then our End ſhall be Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſting Life. Let us learn this Leſſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom our Horſe (for the Lord ſends us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o School to the Bruit Creatures) tho' <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſeem weary and tired, yet when he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nows he is come near his Journeys End, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e will mend his Pace, and go with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew Mettle and Courage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>A Traveller is many times put out of his Way by falſe Directions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Chriſtian had need be very Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in his walking, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er his Steps according to the Infallible Rule of God's Word, for he will meet with many Seducers and Oppoſers, who
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40745:15"/> will endeavour to put him out of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> way. The three grand Seducers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Devil, a Man's own Luſts, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Devil, that old and Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Seducer, who ſince he was thrown o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Heaven himſelf, makes it his work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> keep others from thence, and to lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> poor Souls from the Kingdom of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to his own Kingdom of Darkneſs. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> old Serpent deceived our firſt Parent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and led them out of the way, and ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Paradiſe</hi> too. He is ſaid to deceiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 9.</note> the whole World. He hath <hi>mille fallen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> artes,</hi> a thouſand arts to deceive poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Souls: he hath his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Devices; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 11. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 24.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Wiles or Methods; his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Depths; his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Snares. All the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to deceive poor Souls, and to lead the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> out of their way. Sometimes he tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>forms <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 7.</note> himſelf into an Angel of Light<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſometimes appears as a roaring Lyon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5, 8.</note> now he tempts to Preſumption, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> anon to Deſpair: In Youth he tel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thee it is too ſoon to be Religious, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in old Age he tells thee it is too la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> But his chief Artifice is to miſrepreſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> both the way of Holineſs, and the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Sin; the former he repreſents as<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> difficult, unpleaſant, and a melanchol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40745:15"/> way; the latter as guilded, and ſugared over with all the Sweets of Pleaſure and Delight: He will tell thee, That the one is a broad and eaſie way, the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrait and narrow way: but he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot tell thee that the broad way leads <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 13, 14.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Deſtruction, and the narrow way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eads to Life. He will tell thee that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f thou will walk in his way, thou ſhalt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave Riches enough, but if thou walkeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the way of God, thou muſt look to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eet with Poverty, Hunger, Thirſt, Tears, Hatred, Separation and Reproach; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut he will not tell thee, that Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounceth a Woe to the <hi>firſt,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounceth <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. 20.</note> the laſt to be Bleſſed. He will tell thee that the way of Sin is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rowed with Roſes; but he will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell thee, that Hell is at the end of that way: He will tell thee, that the way of Holineſs is ſtrowed with Thorns; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e will not tell thee, that Heaven is at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he end of that way. Well then, Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow-Travellers, as one adviſeth well in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nother caſe, take heed of <hi>keeping</hi> the Devils Counſel, ſo I caution thee in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his caſe, take heed of <hi>taking</hi> the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ils Counſel, for he never ceaſeth to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ervert the right ways of the Lord. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 10</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another grand Seducer, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40745:16"/> a dangerous, is the <hi>Luſts of thine own Heart:</hi> If thou conſult with theſe, thou wilt never get to <hi>Heaven;</hi> they will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe thee to take the way of Eaſe, of Self-pleaſing, of Self-preſervation, and to ſhun the ways wherein there are ſo many ſtrict Duties to be performed; ſo many ſevere Precepts to be obſerved; ſo many Hardſhips to be ſuffered. They will perſuade thee not to part with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent things, for future inviſible things, and ſuch things as thy Senſes tell thee are full of ſweetneſs and delight, for ſuch things as thou didſt never ſee, but only haſt heard of; not to let go Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Comforts, which thou haſt in hand and poſſeſſion, for ſuch as thou haſt only in hope and expectation: And by ſuch falſe Suggeſtions will they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, like an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> to lead thee out of thy way; then if thou meet with Sufferings and Perſecutions (as thou wilt be ſure to do, if thou art in the right way) thou wilt be ready to make a <hi>ſtand,</hi> (as the Traveller doth when he comes to a croſs Way,) and to enquire which is thy way: Then if thou conſult with Fleſh and Blood, that will be ſure to ſhew thee a falſe way: That will cry out, Save thy ſelf, ſave thy
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40745:16"/> Eſtate, ſave thy Liberty, ſave thy Life, but <hi>no</hi> ſave thy Soul: That will ſay, Pity thy Wife, pity thy Children, pity thy Family, but <hi>no</hi> pity thy Soul. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Chriſtian, ſtop thine Ears againſt theſe <hi>Syrens,</hi> unleſs thou haſt a mind to leave the way of Life, and to be led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way of Death and Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Another grand Seducer is the <hi>World,</hi> in which <hi>one</hi> indeed are a World of Seducers; I ſhall mention <hi>Three,</hi> whom I would caution a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, who ſeriouſly deſires to keep in Heavens way, to take heed of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Covetous Worldling,</hi> who makes <hi>Mammon</hi> his God, and can think of no greater happineſs, than great Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions and large Revenues, than full Barns and full Bags: If thou take his Advice, he will perſuade thee to take the way of Profit, to heap up Riches, to add Houſe to Houſe, and Land to Land, thou ſhalt have the Reputation of a wiſe Man whileſt thou liveſt, and leave a great Subſtance to thy Babes when thou dieſt. <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> Look to thy <hi>Map-Book,</hi> and thou ſhalt ſee that this is as far from thy way, as the <hi>Eaſt</hi> is from the <hi>Weſt,</hi> or as <hi>Heaven</hi> is from <hi>Hell;</hi> there thou ſhalt find that thou
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40745:17"/> 
                  <hi>canſt not love God and Mammon;</hi> That <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 24. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>if any Man love the World, the love of the Father is not in him;</hi> That <hi>it is eaſier for a Camel to go through the Eye of a Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, than for a Rich Man to enter into the Kingdom of God;</hi> That tells thee, That <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 8. 36. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 4.</note> if it were poſſible for thee to <hi>gain the whole World to thy ſelf, with the loſs of thy Soul,</hi> thou wouldſt make but a bad bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: That tells thee, That Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is Idolatry, and that it is Spiritual Adultery too; For as the Love of an Harlot with-draws the Heart from a Lawful Wife, ſo the Love of the <hi>World</hi> with-draws the Heart from God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another Seducer, or Setter, that the <hi>World</hi> employs to turn <hi>Chriſtians</hi> out of their way, is the <hi>Voluptuous Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure,</hi> who can fancy no other Heaven but to ſatisfie his Luſts, and to wallow in Pleaſures (and indeed it is all the Heaven he is like to have:) If thou hearken to him, he will counſel thee to indulge thy Luſts, to pamper thy Fleſh, to take thy fill of Pleaſure while thou may'ſt, while thou haſt Youth and Time. <hi>Ede, bibe, lude, poſt mortem nulla voluptas.</hi> Eat, drink and play, after Death no pleaſure, (and indeed there is none for ſuch as he.) He will tell
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40745:17"/> thee how ſweet and delightful his way is, and that Stage-Plays, Dancing, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, Drinking, Drabbing, are other manner of Delights than thine, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to be poring in a Book all Day, to be running after Sermons, to be Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and alone in thy Cloſet, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thy Body with Faſting. Well, <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> look to thy Rule again, which is a ſure Rule, and cannot deceive thee, which tells thee; Men are in an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate State, while they are ſerving divers Luſts and Pleaſures, that are rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 3.</note> amongſt the vileſt Sinners; and thoſe that are furtheſt out of the way, are <hi>thoſe that are lovers of pleaſures more</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>than lovers of God:</hi> That will tell thee, that the Prodigal was out of his way, (and out of his Wits too) when he took his Journey in a far Country, and there <hi>waſted his Subſtance in riotous Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 15. 11.</note> and with Harlots. And when he came to himſelf, then he left theſe Courſes, and returned to his Father. There thou ſhalt find, that <hi>Moſes choſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>rather to ſuffer Affliction with the People of God, then to enjoy the Pleaſures of Sin for a Seaſon.</hi> But there is one Place, which if there were no more were enough to fright thee from hearkening to theſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40745:18"/> and from following their Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>Rejoyce O Young Man in thy Youth, and let thine Heart chear thee in the Days of thy Youth, and walk in the ways of thy Heart, and in the ſight of thine Eyes; but know that for all theſe things, God will bring thee into Judgment.</hi> So that thou feeſt theſe Sons of Pleaſure are not in the way of Life, but in the way of Death; and are like thoſe Fiſhes which the Hiſtorian reports of, that they ſport themſelves ſo long in the Shallows of the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> till the ſwiftneſs of the Stream carries them into the Dead Sea where they all periſh. They who are for a <hi>ſhort Life and a Merry,</hi> will meet with a long Death and a Sad one: Earthly Pleaſures will be followed with Hells Torments; The Rich Man, who had lived ſo high was brought to a ſhort Dyet: Thoſe that cannot live without Pleaſures here, muſt live without Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for ever.</p>
               <p>And here by way of Digreſſion, I heartily wiſh ſome Eloquent <hi>Appollos,</hi> ſome powerful Orator would ſpeak this Caution ſo loud, that all the young Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants in <hi>England</hi> might hear it, who (for the Generality of them) live as if they had been brought up in the School
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40745:18"/> of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> and not in the School of Chriſt; as if they had drank of <hi>Circes</hi> Cup, and were turned into Swine; they ſo drown and ſoak themſelves in Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that they unfit and incapacitate themſelves, not only for the Service of God, but alſo for their King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: It is a ſad Conſideration to think, what Privy Councellours, what Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, what Magiſtrates we are like to have in another Age.</p>
               <p>A Third Seducer thou wilt meet with in the World is the <hi>Ambitious Perſon,</hi> who like the <hi>Camelion</hi> lives upon Air, upon the breath of the Prince, and the applauſe of the People, who knows no other Heaven but the Princes Smile, no other Hell but his Frowns. If thou ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thy ſelf to him for Direction in thy Way, what Courſe will he adviſe thee to, but that crooked Path that himſelf walketh in? He will adviſe thee to take the way that leads to Honour and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment in the World: He will tell thee the only Happineſs is to be the Princes Favourite, and the Peoples Darling, to have the uppermoſt Rooms at Feaſts, and the chief Seats in all Conventions, and greetings in the Market, and to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of Men <hi>Rabbi,</hi> to have the Cap and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:40745:19"/> the Knee; where ever thou comeſt to have all Men bow to thee; <hi>Digito mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrari &amp; dicier hic eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Chriſtian look to thy Rule, and thou wilt never be deluded with this Pageantry: Thou wilt never be led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Fools Paradice, that will ſhew thee the way to true Honour, <hi>Them that Honour me, I will Honour. Abraham,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes, Paul,</hi> theſe were honourable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Friend of God; <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Servant of the Lord; <hi>Paul,</hi> a Servant of Jeſus Chriſt. Theſe are other manner of Titles of Honour, than the greateſt Grandees on Earth ever at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> who ſtiled himſelf King of Kings. <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> that Reigned <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezra</hi> 7. 12. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 1. 1.</note> from <hi>India</hi> to <hi>Aethiopia</hi> over an hundred twenty ſeven Provinces, The Great <hi>Turk,</hi> The Great <hi>Mogul,</hi> The Emperour of the <hi>Weſt,</hi> The Emperour of the World, are poor, empty, airy, Titles, in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of this, <hi>The Servant of the Lord.</hi> All his Servants are Favourites, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them is a King, and when all Earthly Crowns ſhall fade and wither, they ſhall have a never fading Crown of Glory, <hi>This Honour have all his Saints.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. 9</note> Then Chriſtian thy Rule will tell thee, what end the way of Ambition uſually
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40745:19"/> leads to in this Life. What became of <hi>Herod</hi> who was the Peoples Darling? What became of <hi>Haman</hi> who was the Princes higheſt Favourite? the one when the People had cryed him up for a God, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 22, 23. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 5. 11.</note> died like a Beaſt, and was devoured of Worms: The other, when he had boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one Day, how highly the King had advanced him above all his Princes and Servants; was the next Day advanced to a Gallows fifty Cubits high, where he ended his Life and Honour, in a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and moſt Ignominious Death. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he hath read but little Hiſtory, (nay he hath lived but a little while in the World) who cannot by his own Experience add many Preſidents of this Kind, which ſhould be as ſo many Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of Salt to ſcare thee from this way, <hi>Whoſoever exalts himſelf ſhall be abaſed:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 11. <hi>Job</hi> 24. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>They are exalted for a little while, but are gone, and brought low, they are taken out of the Way as all others.</hi> It was a ſaying worthy of that Chriſtian Emperour <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoſius,</hi> He rejoyced more that he was a Member of the Church of God, then <note place="margin">Gaudere ſe magis quod eſſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Dei quam quod eſſet Caput Imperii.</note> that he was an Emperour of the whole World.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40745:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>A Careful Traveller is much grieved, when he finds himſelf to be out of his Way, and haſtens to get into it again; and is never quiet, till he hath recovered it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SO is it with every Chriſtian that is Travelling towards Heaven. 1. He is exceedingly grieved, when he finds himſelf out of his Way. 2. He haſts, and is reſtleſs, till he get into it again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> When by the Violence of Satans Temptation, or by the Prevalency of Corruption, or by the Allurements of the World, he hath been drawn aſide out of the Way of Holineſs into the By-Paths of Sin: How is this Soul filled with Godly Sorrow and Humiliation? What Sighs and Groans? What Cryes and Tears? What Complaints and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations? What Self-abhorrency and Self-condemnation might you hear, were you at his Cloſet Door, when he is pouring out his melting Soul before God? Nay ſometimes he is like to be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40745:20"/> up with overmuch Sorrow; He cries out, he is loſt and undone, that he ſhall never recover his Journeys end, that he ſhall never get to Heaven: Was it not thus with <hi>David,</hi> when he had ſo foully loſt his way. <hi>My Sin is ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, I am weary of my Groaning, all</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>the Night make I my Bed to ſwim, I Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my Couch with my Tears. My Heart</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>is ſmitten, and withered like Graſs, ſo that I forget to eat my Bread:</hi> His Grief was ſuch, that he could neither Eat nor Sleep. Next hear <hi>Ephraim</hi> bemoaning himſelf, <hi>Surely after I was turned I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>and after that I was inſtructed, I ſmote upon my Thigh, I was aſhamed, yea even confounded,</hi> &amp;c. Then conſider <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> when fear of Suffering and Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence had led him out of the Way, and made him deny and forſwear his Lord and Maſter, <hi>He went out and wept bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. laſt.</note> I ſhall add one more Inſtance, and that is of the Church: It were enough to melt an Heart of Stone ſeriouſly to conſider her doleful Complaints in the Book which is called <hi>Lamentations:</hi> You may there ſee, that the ground of it was becauſe they had departed from God and his Ways, the whole Book is a Proof of this; but I ſhall Name a few places to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40745:21"/> ſhew you her Grief: <hi>She weepeth ſore in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 2, 4, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>the Night, and her Tears are on her Cheeks, her Prieſts ſigh, her Virgins are afflicted, and ſhe is in bitterneſs. Behold and ſee, if there be any Sorrow like to my Sorrow. Mine Eyes do fail with Tears, my Bowels</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lam.</hi> 2. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>are troubled, my Liver is poured upon the Earth. Mine Eyes trickle down and ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not without any Intermiſſion:</hi> Here you <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. 49.</note> have ſomething of her Grief, but you may have much more if you read that Book; then to give you a few Places; which ſhew the ground of all this Sorrow and Complaining: <hi>For the Multitude of your Tranſgreſſions, her Children are gone</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 5, 8, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>into Captivity. Jeruſalem hath grievouſly Sinned. The Lord is Righteous, I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled againſt his Commandment. I am i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Diſtreſs, my Bowels are troubled, my Hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 20.</note> 
                  <hi>is turned within me;</hi> why ſo? <hi>For I have</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 42, <hi>ver.</hi> 22. <hi>ver.</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>grievouſly rebelled. We have tranſgreſſed and rebelled: It is of the Lords Mercie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that we are not conſumed;</hi> She confeſſeth it was the Iniquity of the Daughter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her People, for the Sins of her Prophets, and the Iniquity of her Prieſts: <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Crown is fallen from our Head, wo unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>that we have ſinned:</hi> and in the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Book, the laſt Verſe but on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they Pray, <hi>Turn thou us unto thee O Lord
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40745:21"/> and we ſhall be turned:</hi> By which you ſee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere was the great Cauſe of her Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation, that they were gone out of their Way; therefore they Pray to be turned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto it again: They had departed from God, and Pray to be turned to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; ſo that the firſt Point is clear. That every Child of God, he is making <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or Heaven, and exceedingly grieved and afflicted, when he finds himſelf out of the Way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> As a Traveller haſteth into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Way again, and is never quiet, till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e hath recovered it: So it is with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y true Chriſtian indeed, a Wicked Man when he is in the Ways of Sin, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>isfying his Luſts, he is where he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; he is in his proper Element; if he might Sin Eternally, he would deſire no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etter Life: but it is far otherwiſe with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Child of God, he finds little eaſe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Ways of Sin; when he is drawn out of the Ways of Holineſs, he is out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Element, he hath no more quiet then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Fiſh out of the Water: A wicked Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olls Sin <hi>under his Tongue</hi> like a ſweet Morſel, and delights to feed upon it, as <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 20. 12.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Swine upon Husks; but that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Sinners Meat, is the Saints Poyſon; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd if he hath at any Time Taſted or
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40745:22"/> Sipt of it, he is never quiet till he hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Vomited it up again by true Repentance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> A Swine lies wallowing in the Mire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with Delight and Content; but if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sheep ſtep into it, he makes all the haſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he can to get out of it: When the Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal came to himſelf, and his Eyes were o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pened to ſee, that he had been out of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Way; Then farewel Pots and Harlot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he could feed upon ſuch husks no long<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er; but reſolves to return to his Father<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Houſe, who had Bread enough for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his Servants. When <hi>David</hi> had ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out of his Way, into thoſe vile Way<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Adultery and Murder, we ſee ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> little quiet he had, he ſaith, <hi>I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>roared by reaſon of the diſquietneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Heart: All my Bones are out of Joynt,</hi> (an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſure then he could have but little eaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but though Bones out of Joynt be ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> painful, yet broken Bones are mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> painful, nay, he Complains of broke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Bones too; but if a Man have quiet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 8. <hi>Prov.</hi> 18. 14.</note> his Spirit, <hi>he will ſuſtain his bodily Infi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mities, but a wounded Spirit, who can bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> But he was deeply wounded in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit too? <hi>My Soul alſo is ſore vexed but thou, O Lord! How long?</hi> He com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plains <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. 3.</note> again and again, <hi>Why art thou ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42. 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>down, O my Soul! and why art thou dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40745:22"/> within me. My Soul melteth away for Heavineſs: Strengthen me according to thy Word.</hi> I could likewiſe tell you, what diſquiet the Spouſe was in, when ſhe had refuſed to open to her Beloved, how ſhe ran up and down ſearching and enquiring after him; and was never qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et till ſhe found and enjoyed him again; but this is enough to ſhew, that a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soul that is Travelling towards Heaven is never quiet, when he finds himſelf out of Heavens way (that is the way of Holineſs.) He can have no more eaſe and quiet in his Soul, than he who hath all his Bones broken, or out of Joynt, can have in his Body. Therefore Fellow-Traveller, let us take heed how we go out of our Way into the crooked Paths of Sin, but if we have by Violence of Temptation, or Power of Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on been drawn aſide; let us ſpeedily and heartily repent, and be ſoundly hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for our Backſliding, and let us give our Souls no reſt, till we have again turned our Feet into the Way of Peace; and then I ſhall give thee further Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the next Obſervation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:40745:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>A Traveller, having been once out of his Way, will be the more wary and careful ever after to keep it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND doth not every Relapſe of Gods Children make them more watchful and vigilant for the Future: Doth not every fall they take make them look the better to their Footing? Doth not ever Sin they commit encreaſe their hatred of Sin in their Souls? We have a Proverb, <hi>A burnt Child dreads the Fire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> What is the Reaſon? But becauſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fall into it, did breed him ſo much Pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Smart; ſurely falling into Sin bring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the Children of God ſo much Pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Anguiſh, that they dread it as much as the Fire of Hell; and therefore, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they recover out of it, they will tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heed how they fall into it again: As <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Bird that hath broken looſe out of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Snare of the Fowler, will ſcarce be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in it a ſecond Time. He is little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Word or Way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, that hath not made this Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40745:23"/> that the fall or falls of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (being ſanctified by him that can bring Good out of Evil, and hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>That all things ſhall work together for good to them that love God)</hi> have done them good. They have awakened and quickened them to a more circumſpect walking, they have been the more live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their Duties, more diligent in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and more zealous in ſuffering the Will of God; they have been the more careful to keep out Sin ever after. As it is with a Garriſon, if the Enemies have entred within their Works and repulſed them, they will fortifie that place, where the Enemy made a Breach, more ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than before; ſo it is with a Chriſtian, if any of his Senſes, as for Inſtance, his Ear, or his Eye, which have been inlets to Sin, he will for the future ſet a ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Watch upon them; he will ſtop his Ears againſt all corrupt and unclean Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, he will with <hi>Job, Make a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with his Eyes;</hi> and with <hi>David,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 31. 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 37.</note> beg of God <hi>To turn away his Eyes from beholding Vanity:</hi> If his Tongue cauſe him to offend, he will bridle it up, and beg of God to ſet a Watch before the Door of his Lips: If his Heart betrayed him, he will henceforth ſet a double
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40745:24"/> Guard upon it; that is, he will himſelf keep it with all Diligence, and will ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly beg of God to undertake the keeping of it: The falls of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren have the ſame Effect upon them, that <hi>Pauls</hi> Letter had upon the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> It makes them ſorry after a Godly <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 11.</note> Manner, and this Godly Sorrow, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, what carefulneſs it works in them, yea what clearing of themſelves, yea what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, yea what fear, yea what vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſire, yea what zeal, yea what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; in all things ye have approved your ſelves to be clear in this Matter:</hi> So that it may be truly ſaid of true Chriſtians, that they get ground by their ſtumbling; and as to this Caſe, We may Anſwer this Queſtion of our Saviour Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, and ſay, That Men may <hi>gather Grapes of Thorns, and Figs of Thiſtles;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 16.</note> that God with whom nothing is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible by ſanctifying the falls of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (which are in themſelves Evil) can make them to bring forth Fruit, as Godly Sorrow, Self-abaſement, Care and Watchfulneſs, Diligence and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity in the ways of God: In a Word, they make them more Holy, Humble, Heavenly-minded ever after. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Pride brought him to his Fall, and his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40745:24"/> Fall broke the Neck of his Pride; ſee how Humble he was grown, how his Self-confidence was taken down, when our bleſſed Saviour asked him, <hi>Simon loveſt thou me more then theſe?</hi> (He would no more of that) more then theſe? He could tell Chriſt before, <hi>Though all Men forſake thee, yet will not I.</hi> But now he gives a more humble, modeſt Anſwer, <hi>Lord, thou knoweſt that I love thee.</hi> The Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> when ſhe had by her drowſineſs and neglect of her Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved cauſed him to withdraw, ſhe was reſtleſs, till ſhe had found him again, but when ſhe had recovered him, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved never to let him go more, <hi>I found</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>him whom my Soul loves, I held him faſt and would not let him go.</hi> So it is with every Saint after his recovery from a Fall, he labours to lay faſter hold on Jeſus Chriſt, and to keep more cloſe to his Holy Ways all his Life after: This is a Truth, and a ſweet Truth. But I dare not leave it without this Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let none turn this Rich Grace of God into wantonneſs, this precious Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial into Poyſon. Would any but a mad-Man go and break his Bones, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hears that a broken Bone well cured is ſtronger then before. Hearken
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40745:25"/> what the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Shall we Sin that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Grace may abound? God forbid:</hi> Sure thoſe that belong to God will make a better uſe of his Grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Every Traveller is deſirous to have as much good Company with him in his Journey as he can, eſpecially of his Relations and Friends.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NO Child of God deſires to go to Heaven alone, but is of his Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Mind; <hi>Would have all Men come to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>the Knowledge of the Truth and be ſaved:</hi> And therefore he will be perſwading Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, Friends, Acquaintance, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, Servants, and all with whom he converſeth to keep him Company in the way of Salvation: Certainly who ever is truly converted himſelf, will labour for the Converſion of others. When <hi>Andrew</hi> had found the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> or rather was found of him, he finds out his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 1. 41.</note> 
                  <hi>Simon,</hi> and brings him to Chriſt. When our Saviour had called <hi>Philip,</hi> he <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 1. 45.</note> ſeeks out <hi>Nathanael,</hi> that he might par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40745:25"/> of the ſame Mercy with him. If that Rich Man (he was Rich indeed on <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 16.</note> Earth, but Poor enough in Hell) if he, I ſay, was ſo ſollicitous, that his Brethren might not come to that Place of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment where he was; much more, and upon a better account, will thoſe who are going to Heaven themſelves be ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous that their Brethren may come to that Place of bliſs where they Hope to be. A Magiſtrate, who is going to Heaven, will labour to have all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to go with him: A Miniſter all his People, a Parent all his Children, a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter all his Family, and all his Servants: And every real Chriſtian, all his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and all his Friends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> A Godly Ruler or <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> who rules in Righteouſneſs and the fear of the Lord, will endeavour to bring all his People to fear the Lord, and to have all his Subjects become the Subjects of Chriſt: As it was matter of great Joy to <hi>David,</hi> when he went with the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to the Houſe of God; ſo it is to every Gracious Prince, when he can carry a great Train with him to Heaven. <hi>Moſes</hi> the Servant of the Lord endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make all the People, over whom God had made him Governour,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40745:26"/> the Servants of the Lord; he laboured not only to lead them to an Earthly, but to the Heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi> How faithfully doth he acquaint them with the whole Will of God! How ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſtrictly doth he charge them to walk in all his Ways, and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments! How zealouſly doth he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.</note> them when they go out of the Way! And how importunately doth he beg of God to Pardon all their Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 31, 32.</note> and doth not this ſhew, that he deſired to have them to Heaven with him. <hi>Joſhua</hi> his Succeſſor walked in his Steps, and did not only faithfully ſerve God himſelf, but laboured to make all under his Conduct and Government to ſerve him alſo, and he was very ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in it; for it is written, <hi>That Iſrael</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>ſerved the Lord all the Days of Joſhua;</hi> and ſo careful was he that they ſhould continue walking in the Ways of God; that when he was taking leave of them, and this World, and was going to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, he Summons all the Tribes to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before him; and gives them moſt Holy and Heavenly Exhortations to keep and to do all that was Written in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and not to turn there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, to the Right Hand or to the Left
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40745:26"/> but to cleave to the Lord their God, as they had done to that Day; and much to that Purpoſe, which you may find in the two laſt Chapters of <hi>Joſhua;</hi> by which you may ſee how careful he was to have them to walk with him in the Way of God, while he Lived, and that they ſhould perſevere in thoſe Ways when he was Dead; he deſired to have their Company on Earth and in Heaven. <hi>David</hi> a Man after Gods own Heart, he walked ſo exactly in the Ways of God himſelf; there it is ſaid, <hi>He turned not aſide from any thing he commanded him all</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 15. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>the Days of his Life, ſave only in the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of</hi> Uriah. And he deſired, that not only all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but that all the World might keep him Company in this Good and Holy Way: And therefore he begs of God, <hi>That his Ways may be known up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, and his ſaving Health among all</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 67. 2, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Nations. Let the People Praiſe thee, O God, let all the People Praiſe thee.</hi> And as his Hearts deſire was to ſee all Men walking in the Way to Heaven with him: So was his Righteous Soul grieved, when he ſaw People go out of that Way: For he ſaith, <hi>Rivers of Tears run</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 136.</note> 
                  <hi>down mine Eyes, becauſe Men keep not thy Law.</hi> Good <hi>Joſiah</hi> did not think it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40745:27"/> 
                  <hi>To make a Covenant before the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, to walk after the Lord, and keep his Commandments with all his Heart, and with all his Soul, but he cauſed all</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem <hi>and</hi> Benjamin <hi>to ſtand to it;</hi> he was not Content to ſerve the Lord alone, but he made all <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſerve the Lord. So that you ſee, that Godly Magiſtrates will endeavour to have all their Subjects to Heaven with them. Though it be ſaid of Earthly Kings, that they will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of no Partners in the Crown; yet it may be truly ſaid of thoſe Kings, who look after an Heavenly Kingdom; that they would have all to partake with them in the Crown of Glory. But then,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, A Godly Miniſter</hi> will labour to carry all his Flock to Heaven with him; that he may ſay when he comes there, <hi>behold here am I, and the Children</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>which the Lord hath given me.</hi> How doth he Preach to them, Pray for them, and weep over them; how doth he beat his Brains, break his Sleep, and even ſpend his Strength and Spirits, that he may bring them to walk in the Way of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, which he goes before them in and to be Followers of him as he is o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt. <hi>Paul</hi> that bleſſed Apoſtle wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an eminent Example of this, what Pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:40745:27"/> did he take? What Dangers did he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo? What a Circuit of Ground did he traverſe on Earth, that he might bring Souls to Heaven, and that all that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 15. 19.</note> heard him might be ſuch as he was? How zealous was he to have all his Countrey-men to Heaven with him? As appears, <hi>Brethren my Hearts deſire</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>and Prayer to God for</hi> Iſrael <hi>is, that they might be ſaved;</hi> and by that Hyperbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 6.</note> Expreſſion, <hi>I could wiſh my ſelf accurſed from Chriſt for my Brethren, my Kinſmen according to the Fleſh;</hi> and this Zeal of his was not confined only to the <hi>Jews,</hi> but extended to the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> alſo, whoſe Apoſtle he was, he ſaith, <hi>He teſtifies to the</hi> Jews, <hi>and alſo to the</hi> Greeks, <hi>Repentance towards God, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Faith towards our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> So that he ſhewed both the Way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; he ſaith, <hi>He went about teaching</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 20.</note> 
                  <hi>them, not only Publickly, but from Houſe to Houſe. That he ceaſed not to warn eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 31.</note> 
                  <hi>one Day and Night with Tears.</hi> I might inſtance in all the reſt of the Apoſtles, who did all labour abundantly, though <hi>Paul did labour more abundantly than they</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>all.</hi> Nay, There is not one faithful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt in the World, but makes it his Work to draw Souls to that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40745:28"/> whither he is going: They can all make their Appeal to the People, <hi>You know how we exhorted every one of you, as</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>a Father doth his Children: That you walk worthy of God, that hath called you to his Kingdom and Glory:</hi> And when they can prevail with them ſo to walk, it is their Joy and their Crown of Rejoycing. We <note place="margin">
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 19.</note> may judge without breach of Charity, that Miniſter not to be going to Heaven himſelf, who cares not whether his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple go to Heaven or Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> There is the ſame deſire in all Family Relations. How will the Converted Husband, labour with the Wife of his Boſom, to draw together in the ſame Yoke of Chriſt with him, that they may walk hand in hand to Heaven; He did never ſo importunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wooe her to be married to himſelf, as he will wooe her to be married to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Parent who is himſelf going towards Heaven, will labour to carry all his Children with him; and therefore will Pray with them, and for them; and will carefully endeavour to <hi>bring them up in the Nurture and Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Lord, and to Train them in the way, wherein they ſhould go.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:40745:28"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> A Maſter of a Family who is walking in Heavens Way himſelf, will have all his Servants to walk in the ſame Way with him; He will labour to make them all the Servants of the Lord Jeſus, to make his Houſe a little Houſe of God; that it may be ſaid of him, as it was of <hi>Philemon, The Church which is in thy Houſe.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note> We know what the Lord ſaith of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, I know</hi> Abraham <hi>that he will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>his Children, and his Houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the Way of the Lord.</hi> We know alſo what was <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s Reſolution, <hi>I and my Houſe will ſerve the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord.</hi> And what <hi>David's</hi> was, <hi>He that walketh in a perfect Way ſhall ſerve me:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.</note> 
                  <hi>He that worketh Deceit ſhall not dwell in my Houſe; He that telleth lyes ſhall not tarry in my ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Every real Chriſtian will be earneſtly perſuading all his Neighbours and Acquaintance to accompany him in his Journey toward Heaven. What the Poet ſaith of the natural Birth, may be truly ſaid of the Spiritual Birth. <hi>Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur indigne per quam non naſcitur alter. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy to be Born is he, By whom no others Born be.</hi> So he is not worthy to be new Born, who is not Inſtrumental to make others new Born; He deſerves
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40745:29"/> not the Name of a Chriſtian (and ſure he hath but the Name) who doth not heartily endeavour to draw others to Chriſt. I appeal to all who are going Heaven-ward themſelves, whether they have not a longing deſire to get all the Company they can to Heaven with them; and it is no wonder, if we conſider how ſweet the Work is, and what a bleſſed Reward is promiſed to it. <hi>And they that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>be Wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firmament, and they that turn many to Righteouſneſs, as the Stars for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> So now it is clear, that herein the Earthly and the Heavenly Traveller a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that both labour to have as much Company with them as they can.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>A Traveller in his Journey will keep Company with ſuch and ſuch only as are going the ſame way that he is, and to the ſame Place.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND this Chriſtian, calls for thy ſpecial Imitation, if thou art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved for Heaven, thou muſt keep Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40745:29"/> with ſuch as are going Heavens way, and ſhun the Company of thoſe who are going in the contrary way to Hell and Deſtruction; I ſhall begin with the laſt firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Thou muſt ſhake Hands with thoſe who were thy old Companions in the Ways of Sin; <hi>Can two walk toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, except they be agreed?</hi> And what <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amos</hi> 3. 3.</note> agreement can there be between the Children of Light, and the Children of Darkneſs; between the Children of God, and the Children of the Devil; between thoſe who are reſolved for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and thoſe who are at agreement with Hell? Will Sheep flock together with Swine, or Doves with Vultures? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. 15.</note> Who would make thoſe his Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on Earth, who muſt be Companions of the Devil and his Angels in Hell for ever? Therefore as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>I have not ſat with vain Perſons,</hi> ſo do thou ſay, <hi>I will not walk with vain Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</hi> thou wilt be ſure to receive no good by them, but wilt be in danger to receive much hurt. For it is as impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for one in pure White to embrace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chimney-Sweeper, and not to be ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ied, as for a Man to hold familiar and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utimate Converſe with Prophane Men,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40745:30"/> and not be defiled: That Man is got half Way to Heaven, that is rid of his wicked Companions. The general Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of Chriſtians will Seal to this Truth, that when God hath changed the Heart, and a Man hath changed his Courſes, he will alſo change his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. <hi>Paul,</hi> when the Scales were fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len off his Eyes, and he was brought in to the right Way, he would have no more Familiarity with his great Friends the Chief Prieſts, nor with his old Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Companions, and he left their Friendſhip. So they became his bitter Enemies, and when he left perſecuting the Saints of God, they fell to perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of him. We read indeed of good <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> that he entred into a ſtrict League and Intimacy with wicked <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab;</hi> but we know that he was out of his Way when he did ſo, and it was like to coſt him his Life; and though God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved his Life, yet he was diſpleaſed with his Act, as you may ſee in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. 22.</note> Now this is one thing, that thou muſt imitate the Traveller in; namely, thou muſt ſhun the Company of thoſe who are going in a contrary Way, But,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thou muſt conſort with thoſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40745:30"/> who are going thy Way; thou muſt not only ſeparate from Sinners, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with Saints: Thou muſt avoid the Society of the wicked, leaſt they hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee in thy Way; and thou muſt aſſociate with the Godly, that they may further thee in thy Way: Thou muſt ſhun the one, that they may not be a Bridle or Curb to hold thee back: Thou muſt embrace the other, that they may be a Spur to quicken thee and put thee forward: It is a common Saying, and it may be called a Traveller's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>An Eloquent or Pleaſant Companion on the Way is inſtead of a Chariot.</hi> And <note place="margin">Facundus comes in Via, pro Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiculo eſt.</note> it may be ſaid, that Godly Companions in the Way to Heaven, are inſtead of <hi>Elias</hi> his Chariot, they will be helpful to thee many ways.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> By their Counſel.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> By their Holy Example.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> By their Heavenly Conference.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> By their faithful Reproofs.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> By their fervent Prayers.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> They will forward thee in thy way to Heaven by their good Counſel and Inſtruction. The Heathen Poet ſpeaks like a Chriſtian in this,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From good men thou wilt learn good things.</hi> And doth not the Word of God ſpeak
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40745:31"/> to the ſame purpoſe from that Divine Proverb, <hi>He that walketh, with wiſe men</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall be wiſe, but a Companion of Fools ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> We know that <hi>Solomons</hi> Wiſe man is the good or the Godly man, and certainly there is no ſuch wiſe Man in the World as he that is wiſe for his Soul and for <hi>Eternity;</hi> ſo here is one bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thou will reap by keeping Company with the Godly, thou wilt have good Counſel and Inſtruction from them, and ſee what a benefit this was to <hi>Jehoaſh, He did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord all his days wherein Jehojada the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 12. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Prieſt inſtructed him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thou wilt be promoted in thy Way by their Holy Example: The Examples of good Men are more taking <note place="margin">Exempla plus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt quam praecepta.</note> than their Inſtruction: Their Practices than their Precepts: He is like to write the faireſt Hand, who writes after the faireſt Copy: If thou canſt ſay with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, I am a Companion of all thoſe that fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 63.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord;</hi> what a Pattern wilt thou have for thy Imitation, when thou doſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their Holy Conveſation; when thou doſt every Day ſee how careful the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are to walk by Rule; how Conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to perform their Duty before Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Man? How Holily they behav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:40745:31"/> themſelves in the World? In their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies? In their Cloſets? In their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings? In every Condition? In every Relation? How Chearfully they do? How Patiently they ſuffer the Will of God? How can this but ſtir up thy Mind to an Holy Emulation? And what an help will this be to thee in thy Way to Heaven?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They will be helpful to thee by their <hi>Heavenly Conference,</hi> As evil Communication corrupts good Manners, ſo good Communication muſt needs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote good Manners: It is ſaid, <hi>The Lips</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 10. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Righteous feed many;</hi> and this is ſweet food indeed. Chriſt ſaith of the Church, <hi>Thy Lips drop as the Honey-comb.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 4. 11</note> What Sweet and Holy Diſcourſes will the Saints of God have, when they meet together? How will they provoke one another to Love and good Works? How will they communicate their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Experiences? How will they like Coals kindle one another, and raiſe up one anothers Affections Heaven-ward? How will they encourage one another to hold and perſevere in the ways of Holineſs, by ſetting forth the Joys and the Glory of that Heavenly Country whether they are all going? As Prophane
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40745:32"/> Wretches never meet, but they harden one another by their lewd and rotten Speeches; ſo the Children of God never do (or at leaſt never ſhould) meet but they Edify one another by their gracious Communications. We may obſerve, that our bleſſed Lord and Saviour aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into Heaven, from Holy Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with his Apoſtles; ſo was <hi>Elijah</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. 19.</note> taken up in his Fiery Chariot, while he was in Holy Conference with <hi>Eliſha.</hi> Now as they went to Heaven, while they were in this Holy Duty; ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 12. 11.</note> it will be a great help to thee in thy Way to Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If thou keep Company with the Saints, they will afford thee no little help by their <hi>Faithful Reproofs.</hi> Hear what the Wiſe Man ſaith, <hi>It is better to hear the Rebukes of the Wiſe, than to hear</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>the Song of Fools. Faithful are the Words</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 27. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>of a Friend, but the Kiſſes of an Enemy are deceitful.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let the Righteous Smite me and it ſhall be a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141. 5</note> 
                  <hi>let him Reprove me and it ſhall be an excellent Oil.</hi> And he loved ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets as <hi>Nathan</hi> and <hi>Gad,</hi> who would faithfully reprove him, when he went out of his Way, and deal plainly with him; and tell him, <hi>Thou art the Man.</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:40745:32"/> It had been well for <hi>Ahab,</hi> if he had done ſo to; if inſtead of hating good <hi>Micaiah</hi> for his faithful dealings, he had hated his Four hundred Court-Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, who ſoothed and flattered him to his Deſtruction. I ſhall relate thee a Story, which is not impertinent, and may not prove unprofitable. There was a Man well known to my ſelf (for he Lived in the ſame Pariſh with me) who being at a Fair or Market (ſome Twelve Miles from his Habitation) Selling his Wares did Swear an Oath, one who heard it did ſtep to him, and whiſpered in his Ear theſe or the like Words: <hi>Friend, Cannot you Sell your Commodities without diſhonouring God? If you ſhould gain a Penny by that Oath, and loſe your own Soul, you would make but a bad Bargain:</hi> Pray think of it. The Man having diſpatched his Market, Rides homeward pondering all the way upon theſe Words, one while he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with himſelf, This Man was a Stranger to me, I know neither his Name nor Face, ſure he could have no other End nor Aim, but my Good. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother while he was much affected with the Manner of delivering the Reproof, in that he did it ſo mildly and private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40745:33"/> as if he were unwilling to put him to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Shame; then he conſidered the Words, and was Convinced that they were a real Truth: The Iſſue was, that ever after this, he left not only his Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but alſo all his other Sins, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a new Man, and did heartily own the Ways of God, and walked uprightly in them to his dying Day. Now as this ſhould encourage and quicken us to a faithful Diſcharge of this Holy Duty; ſo it may ſhew what I am ſpeaking of, namely, what a ſpecial Benefit they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, that walk in Society with the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who will <hi>in any wiſe rebuke their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not ſuffer Sin upon him.</hi> As he <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lev.</hi> 19. 17.</note> who hath a skilful Phyſician always in his Company, hath a great advantage for the preſerving of his bodily Health, becauſe he will oppoſe the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the Diſtemper; ſo hath he a mighty Advantage for his Souls Health, who hath a faithful Reprover always in <note place="margin">Venienti occurrere morbo, &amp; Principiis obſtare.</note> his Company, who <hi>ingruenti malo occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere</hi> ſtop him when he takes his firſt ſtep out of his way, and bring him into his right way again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The Godly will be exceeding helpful to thee by their <hi>ferv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt Trayers.</hi> It is the ſaying of one, That, that Child
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40745:33"/> that hath a ſtock of faithful Prayers laid up for him, hath a Rich Portion; and ſuch a Rich Portion hath every Child of God, for he hath a ſhare in the Prayers of all the Saints upon Earth. And what a Priviledge is this, if we conſider what Promiſes are made to their Prayers, <hi>Ask, and it ſhall be given</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>you,</hi> (it is but ask and have, if we ask not amiſs) <hi>Verily, I ſay unto you, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 16. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>you ſhall ask the Father in my Name he will give it you. The effectual fervent</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Prayer of a Righteous Man will avail much;</hi> and what then will the fervent Prayers of all the Righteous do? <hi>The Eyes of the Lord are upon the Righteous,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>and his Ears are open to their Cry;</hi> which is repeated, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 12. The eminent Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was ſenſible of this, and therefore he begs the Prayers of the Saints for himſelf, and the reſt of the Apoſtles, <hi>Brethren, Pray for us.</hi> And <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ. 5. 25. 2 Theſſ. 3. 1. Heb. 13. 18. Rom.</hi> 15. 30.</note> how vehemently doth he beg it, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you Brethren, for the Lord Jeſus Chriſts ſake, and for the Love of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; that you ſtrive together with me in your Prayers to God for me.</hi> And you may ſee, he counted their Prayers to be very help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and beneficial. <hi>You alſo helping toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor. 1. 11. Phil.</hi> 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>in Prayer. I know that this ſhall turn
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40745:34"/> to my Salvation through your Prayers.</hi> By theſe thou mayſt ſee clearly of what ſingular Benefit the Prayers of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may be to thee, that have ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency with the Great God. And now I have ſhewed thee, how the Chriſtian, who is going towards Heaven, muſt imitate the wiſe Traveller, in parting from thoſe who are going a contrary Way, and keeping Company with thoſe who are going his Way. The <hi>Heathen</hi> Poet could give this Advice.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Converſe thou not with Men whoſe Lives are ill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But let thy Converſe be with good Men ſtill.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>And this agrees with the Holy Word of God, and with the Example of the Man after Gods own Heart; for he ſaith, <hi>Depart from me ye evil Doers, for I will keep the Commandments of my God.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 115.</note> 
                  <hi>I am a Companion of all them that fear thee, and of them that keep thy Precepts.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 63.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:40745:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>He that Travels in a ſtrange Countrey, muſt look to meet with many Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts and Injuries, with many Troubles and Afflictions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Children of God are all <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Pilgrims on the Earth;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 13.</note> they are out of their own Countrey, far from their own home, and from their Fathers Houſe, and therefore, they muſt not think it ſtrange to be uſed like Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. The World had never any good Will for the People of God; our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour hath told us, what we muſt look for from them. <hi>The World hateth you, becauſe you are not of the World, but</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 15. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>I have choſen you out of the World.</hi> And the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> met with many Dangers and Difficulties in their Paſſage towards the Earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſo do the Children of God in their Paſſage through the Wilderneſs of this World towards the Heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi> And this may be ſeen in the Example of all the Saints, that have gone to Heaven before us. I
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40745:35"/> ſhall Inſtance in a few. Good <hi>Jacob</hi> calls his Life a Pilgrimage, and ſaith, <hi>That the Days of it were Few and Evil;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 47. 9.</note> that is, full of Affliction, and ſo they were; He was fain while Young to fly from his own Countrey, or elſe his own Brother would have been his Murderer; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. 41, 42.</note> being gone, what harſh and unfaithful dealings did he meet with from Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Laban?</hi> what hardſhip did he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo Night and Day, and how ill was he requited? <hi>His Wife was changed once,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen. 29. 23. Gen.</hi> 31. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>and his Wages ten Times.</hi> At his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, how terribly was he frighted when he heard of his Brother coming to meet him with four hundred Men? What bitter Croſſes had he afterward in his Children? <hi>Reuben</hi> defiled his Fathers Bed. Gadding <hi>Dinah</hi> was Raviſhed; <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> were Brethren in Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in a cruel and bloody Act; <hi>Judah</hi> committed Inceſt; His Darling <hi>Joſeph</hi> was, as he conceived, Torn in Pieces with Wild Beaſts, and at laſt he muſt part with his Beloved <hi>Benjamin</hi> too, upon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous Terms, or he and his Family muſt periſh with Famine; all theſe things were againſt him, and were like to bring down his Gray-hairs with Sorrow to the Grave; ſo that he might well ſay
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40745:35"/> the Days of his Pilgrimage were evil. Next ſee how it was with <hi>David,</hi> a Man after Gods own Heart, while he was <hi>a Stranger, and a Sojourner here as all his Fathers were.</hi> His Life was ſo full <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. 12.</note> of troubles, that I believe he enjoyed more quiet while he was a Shepherds Boy, then he did all his Life after; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came to the Crown, he was hunted up and down by <hi>Saul;</hi> and after he came to the Crown by <hi>Abſolom:</hi> It were endleſs to give you a particular Relation of his Sorrows, of <hi>Sauls</hi> Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, of <hi>Nabals</hi> Reproaches, <hi>Shimei</hi>'s Railings and Curſings, <hi>Michals</hi> Mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Doegs</hi> Treachery, his great Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Fears while he was with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſh,</hi> his very great Diſtreſs at <hi>Ziglag,</hi> his many bitter Croſſes and Afflictions in his Children and Family, and the trouble he had with his great Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Sons of <hi>Zerviah,</hi> ſo thou ſeeſt what a troubleſome Paſſage he alſo had through this Valley of Tears. I ſhall mention one more in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that is <hi>Job,</hi> a Man who had this Character from the Mouth of God himſelf; <hi>That he was Perfect and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright, and one that feared God, and eſchewed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil:</hi> What entertainment did he meet
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40745:36"/> with, while he was Travelling through this World? How was he uſed by the <hi>Caldeans</hi> and <hi>Sabeans?</hi> What ſad Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel did his Wife give him? What miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 2. 9.</note> Comforters were his Friends to him? But I ſhall not enlarge, for as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>You have heard of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of</hi> Job; ſo I may ſay, we have heard of the Afflictions of <hi>Job.</hi> If thou deſireſt any more Inſtances of Old Teſtament Saints, Read the <hi>11th Chapter</hi> of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> which is called a little Book of Martyrs; and there thou wilt have enough, who all confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>They were Strangers and Pilgrims on Earth.</hi> Then conſider how it was with <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20.</note> New Teſtament Saints, whether they had a more eaſie Journey or a more ſmooth Paſſage. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the bleſſed Apoſtles, who were Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors ſent from the great God of Heaven and Earth, to offer poor ſinful Creatures, Terms and Conditions of Peace, and to beſeech them in <hi>Chriſts ſtead to be reconciled to God;</hi> to proclaim a Pardon, and an Act of Oblivion to Rebels and Traitors, if they will lay down their Arms, and come in, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of it, one would think ſhould be well treated, and kindly dealt with for
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40745:36"/> their Meſſage ſake, but none were treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed worſe where-ever they came, they were uſed like Rogues, they were Whipt and put into the Stocks; nay, as if they had been the greateſt Malefactors, they were caſt into Priſons and Dungeons, they were Stoned, and put to ſeveral kind of Deaths; you may ſee a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of <hi>Pauls</hi> Sufferings. <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. from <hi>ver.</hi> 22. to 30.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall add but one Inſtance more, and that is beyond all the reſt; our bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, when he took our Fleſh upon him, and came into the World upon the moſt bleſſed Errand that ever was, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſave Sinners: What Entertainment did he find here? One would think that if they had no Care of their Souls, yet Chriſts feeding their Bodies, and heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their Diſeaſes, ſhould have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured him very good Quarter among them; but it was far otherwiſe, the Kings of the Earth ſet themſelves, and the Rulers took Counſel together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this <hi>Chriſtum Domini,</hi> this anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lord, the High-Prieſt and Prieſts and People, all conſpired together againſt him, and they never left, till they had brought him to the Croſs: I ſhall forbear to mention his particular
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40745:37"/> Sufferings, becauſe I intend Brevity: But in General, he was perſecuted from the Cradle to the Grave, and though he knew no Sin, yet he knew more Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and Sufferings, then all the Saints that ever were upon the Earth put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: And he hath told us, we muſt look to be troubled as he was. So now <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa. 53. 3. Mat.</hi> 10. 24.</note> this is clear, that the Children of God in this World are like Travellers in a ſtrange Land, where they muſt look to be dealt with as Strangers, and to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer many Injuries and Hardſhips: But Chriſtian, let not this diſcourage thee, for though thou meet with much toil and trouble in the way, yet thou wilt meet with none at the end of it, but with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Reſt, Joy and Glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>He that Travels about Buſineſs, which highly concerns him, reſolves to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> through all Difficulties and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Chriſtians Journey is of vaſt and infinite Concernment to him: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:40745:37"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> about buſineſs of abſolute Neceſſity, that muſt be done or he is undone: It concerns no leſs than the Eternal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Miſery of his immortal Soul: He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Travelling for Heaven, for a Crown, for a Kingdom: He is flying from Hell, from the Wrath to Come, from Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Burnings, and therefore it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns him to Arm himſelf with invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ible Courage, to go through thick and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hin, to overcome all Oppoſitions and Diſcouragements, which he ſhall meet with in the Way; and ſo the Lords Worthies of old have done, <hi>approving</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>themſelves as Servants of God, in much Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ience, in Afflictions, in Neceſſities, in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reſſes, in Stripes, in Impriſonments, in Tumults, in Labours, in Watchings, in Faſtings. A ſlothful Man ſaith, There is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Lyon in the way; Daniel</hi> will not fear <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 26. 13.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o go on, though there be a Den of Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns in his Way; this ſhall not fright <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im, to forbear Praying to his God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough but for a few Days, then to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne Prayer leſs then aforetime. So the Three Children of God, would rather <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.</note> go into the fiery Furnace, then go out of their Way: <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot diſcouraged with Walled Cities, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the Mighty Giants, but they were
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40745:38"/> for Marching into <hi>Canaan;</hi> and they <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 13.</note> only entred-<hi>Canaan,</hi> when all the reſt were ſhut out for their Unbelief. When <hi>Paul</hi> was told by a Prophet, that he ſhould be bound at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and was <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 21.</note> earneſtly diſſwaded from going thither; this could not put him out of his Way, but he anſwers with a brave Chriſtian Reſolution. <hi>I am ready not only to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bound, but to die at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> O that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were ſtill ſuch a Spirit among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans! But alas, there are too many o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Mind of that King of <hi>France,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would venture no further into the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Cauſe of Religion, then he migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> recover the Shore, if a Storm ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe! Truly, <hi>the Children of this Worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>are wiſer in their Generation, then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Children of Light.</hi> I have ſometime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (not without wonder) taken notice o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the great Labour and Induſtry of ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of my Neighbours, who do conſtantl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> once a Week many of them (and ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> twice) all the Year round, Summe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Winter, riſe in the midſt of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Night, and ride to a Market near twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Miles diſtant from them; and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Darkneſs, nor Wind, nor Weather Storms, Rain, Froſt or Snow, can hinde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:40745:38"/> or deter them from their Journey; and all this Pains they take for a poor Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood in the World. O Chriſtian! How may this ſhame thee and me, that we ſhould take leſs Pains for Heaven, than theſe do for Earth; that we ſhould not be more induſtrious for an Eternal Life, than they are for a Temporal? Truly thoſe that profeſs themſelves Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, do the Work of the Lord too negligently, and mind the things of this World too carefully and ſollicitouſly: <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>NR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> That Elegant ſaying is too true.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By Matters as our Work we Ply,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our Work as Matters by the by.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>If there be a Place of Preferment void <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Court, what Riding and Poſting will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here be for it, let the Ways and Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be what they will; and when there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re Heavenly Manſions, when there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> never fading Crown of Glory, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here is a Kingdom that cannot be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en to be had in Heaven, ſhall we ſit ſtill, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r walk on heavily, or be deterred with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e difficulty or unpleaſantneſs of the Way; eſpecially, when it is our own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtake only, that makes the way of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od ſeem unpleaſant and uneaſie, for
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40745:39"/> he hath told us, <hi>That his ways are ways of Ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſantneſs, and all his Paths Peace;</hi> and our Saviour tells us, <hi>That his Yoke is eaſie, and his Burthen light:</hi> If we were Chriſtians indeed, and did live by Faith, and not by Senſe, that one Word <hi>Eternity</hi> would have a greater Influence upon us to make us mend ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pace to Heaven. A <hi>Painter</hi> being ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, why he was accurate and exact, and took ſo much pains, and ſpent ſo much time in drawing his Picture; anſwered, <hi>Pingo Aeternitati,</hi> I Paint for Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Truly Chriſtian, thou maiſt with much more Truth ſay, <hi>Vivo Aeternita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</hi> I Live for Eternity; and therefore thou ſhouldſt take all poſſible Care to walk accurately and exactly, and ſhould<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtick at no Pains or Sufferings, ſo tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> maiſt finiſh thy Courſe with Joy, di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we ſeriouſly conſider, that our Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Condition depends upon the courſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we take here in this World, that if w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> walk in the Way of Holineſs and Righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, we ſhall be Everlaſtingly Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; but if we walk after the faſhion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this World, and after the Luſts of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own Fleſh, we ſhall be Everlaſting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Miſerable; Methinks this ſhould make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to overcome all Oppoſition and Difficu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40745:39"/> that ſo we might ſit down with Chriſt on his Throne, even as Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo overcame, and is ſet down with his Father on his Throne.</p>
               <p>Had we a real and lively belief of the Inviſible Things of the other World (of the Glory of Heaven, and of the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Hell) it would cauſe us to ſlight all the Oppoſition and Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we meet with in the World; <hi>And to run with Patience the Race that is ſet before us: Looking unto Jeſus the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and Finiſher of our Faith, who for the Joy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſs, deſpiſing the ſhame, and is ſet down at the Right Hand of the Throne of God.</hi> I do not wonder, that <hi>Paul,</hi> who was wrapt up into the Third Heavens, did labour more abundantly then all the reſt of the Apoſtles: For a ſight of Heaven would make any Man think no Labour or Pains too great to obtain it: For certainly, what Pains ſoever we take, whatſoever Sufferings we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, Heaven will pay for all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:40745:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>He that makes haſte in his Journey by Galloping or Running, will cauſe all the Dogs in the Countrey to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him with Barking.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND is it not ſo with thoſe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are Journying towards Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If any be more zealous in their Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, more conſcientious in their Practice than others: If they will not only ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from Evil themſelves, but alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade and exhort others ſo to do; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they will be talking of Holineſs where-ever they come, and reproving of Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in whomſoever they find it: How will the Prophane Rabble open their black Mouths againſt ſuch? How will they bark at them, <hi>Tanquam Canis ad Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> like the Dog at the Moon; and why do Dogs bark at the Moon? It i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not, becauſe they ſee her Spots, but he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bright ſhining. So do the Prophan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ones of the World Reproach and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile the Servants of God, not becauſe they ſee their Spots and Blemiſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:40745:40"/> (which themſelves ſee and bewail) but the true Cauſe is, becauſe their bright ſhining Converſation upbraids and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves their Deeds of Darkneſs: If a Man be a cold, or a lukewarm Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, and can be content to let others Sin in quiet (though he will not joyn with them) and will, as they ſay, keep his Religion to himſelf, he may perhaps find fair Quarter in the World, and have the good Word of all his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. But if a Man will reprove their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngodly Deeds, and cannot hold his Peace when he hears his God diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and Blaſphemed; if when he ſees Men take the ready way to damn their own Souls, he cannot but give them warning of it, and will not ſuffer him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o go quietly to Hell; ſuch a Man ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aiſe the cry of the whole Country a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, he ſhall become the Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rds Song, and the Table Talk of all prophane Feaſts and Meetings; He, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch as he is, ſhall be accounted Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Fools, Singular, Cenſorious, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oneous, Enemies to Governours, and what not: Nay, becauſe wicked Men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an find nothing in their Holy Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation whereof juſtly to accuſe them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herefore they will moſt impudently and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40745:41"/> impiouſly invade the Prerogative of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great God, and will undertake to judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Hearts, and to ſay they are all Hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pocrites: But if any one, who hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> been eminent for Profeſſion, do fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any ſcandalous Sin: How will th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whole Kennel open their Mouths in a fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cry, not only againſt their Perſon, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo againſt the whole Party: This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one of your Holy Brethren, this is o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of your great Profeſſors, that would re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove another if he did but Swear a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Oath, or if he did but Drink a mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cup or two with his Friends, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he hath done a great deal worſe himſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you may ſee what they all are, for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are all alike; though ſome can carry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> more cloſely, and ſmoothly then other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> What Reaſon, Ingenuity or Honeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is there in ſuch arguing? <hi>Judas</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Devil; what therefore muſt all Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diſciples be Devils? Surely none b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Devils Schollars would make ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an Argument, beſides by what fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rule do they judge the Perſon offen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? For they judge him by one ſing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Act of his Life (which if he belong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, he will be deeply humbled fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and obtain the Pardon of) when in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mean time they condemn thoſe as ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:40745:41"/> ſorious and uncharitable, who judge their preſent State by a right Rule; namely, by the conſtant courſe and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their whole Converſation. While there be ſo many mocking <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maels,</hi> ſo many Railing <hi>Shimei</hi>'s and Ranting <hi>Rabſhekahs</hi> in the World, the Children of God muſt look for Railing and Reviling. But Chriſtian, deſpiſe them all, and imitate the Traveller, who regards not the Barking of every Cur, but keeps on his Way till he comes to his Journeys end; or rather imitate the generous Horſe, which when the Dogs follow him with Balling, is ſo far from ſlackning his Pace, that he mends it and Gallops on the faſter; ſo let the Calumnies and Slanders of evil Men, cauſe thee to be more careful and wary, that thou go not out of thy Way, and the more reſolutely to hold on thy Way, till thou come to Heaven, where thou ſhalt have Admiſſion, but Dogs ſhall be ſhut out, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:40745:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>He that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakes a long Journey, and through difficult Paſſages, had need to be a ſtrong Man, and well provided for his Journey.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the Application of this, I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſhew.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That the Chriſtians Journey to Heaven, is a long Journey.</item>
                  <item>2. That he will meet with many Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties in his Paſſage.</item>
                  <item>3. That therefore he had need to ſtrengthen and prepare himſelf for it.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> A Chriſtians Journey is a long Journey: It is not a Days Journey, or a Week, or a Months, or a Years Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, but it is a Life's Journey: His Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and his Life ſhould begin, and end together. <hi>We ſhould ſeek the Kingdom of God, and his Righteouſneſs in the firſt Place;</hi> nay, we ſhould ſeek this Firſt and Laſt, and all our Life; all our Days on Earth ſhould be ſpent in fitting us for Heaven, and making us meet to be Partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40745:42"/> We read that the Angel ſaid to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Elijah, Ariſe and eat, for thy Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>is great;</hi> and the Angel ſaid to him the ſecond Time, <hi>Ariſe and eat, for thy Journey is too great for thee: And he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe, and did eat and drink, and went in the Strength of that Meat forty Days and forty Nights unto Horeb the Mount of God.</hi> So I ſay unto thee Chriſtian, ariſe and ſtrengthen thy ſelf with Spiritual Food, for thy Spiritual Journey is great; yea, I ſay unto thee again, ariſe and eat, not of the Bread which Periſheth, but of that which endureth unto Everlaſting Life; for thy Journey is too great for thee, unleſs thou be aſſiſted with Strength from above. Therefore ariſe and feed by Faith on the Lord Jeſus, who is the Bread of Life; ſtrengthen thy ſelf in the Word of God, and the ſweet Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Goſpel, and in the ſtrength of this Meal, thou ſhalt be able to go all the Days and Nights of thy Life, till thou come to Heaven; ſo thou ſeeſt thy Journey is great.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>condly,</hi> Thou wilt meet with many Difficulties and rough Paſſages in thy Way; why elſe doth the Word of God require ſtriving, wreſtling, labouring, working, circumſpect walking, giving
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40745:43"/> all diligence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sure the Way to Heaven is not a ſmooth Way, though it be a clean Way: Thou doſt not know with what hideous and helliſh Temptations Satan may aſſault thee? Thou knoweſt not how impetuous and unruly thy Corruptions may grow? Thou knoweſt not with what outrage and cruelty the World may purſue thee? And therefore, thou hadſt need to ſtrengthen thy ſelf with Zeal and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, leaſt thy Heart fail thee in thy Journey, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port which the Spies brought them. What if thy Faith ſhould be tried as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s was? What if thy Patience ſhould be tried as <hi>Jobs</hi> was? What if thy Love to Chriſt ſhould be tried by this, <hi>viz?</hi> Whether thou wilt leave <hi>Houſe, Brethren, Siſters, Father, Mother,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 29. <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Wife, Children, Lands, and all thou haſt for his ſake and the Goſpels?</hi> What if the fiery Tryal ſhould come upon thee? Or thou muſt <hi>reſiſt unto Blood, ſtriving againſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Sin?</hi> Would not theſe things try what mettle thou art made of? And would they not require Strength and Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to undergo them? And theſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, thou maiſt meet with in thy way to Heaven, if thou come there. And therefore,</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:40745:43"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Since we have a great Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to go, and ſince we may (nay we muſt) expect to meet with ſo many and ſo great Difficulties in our Way; had we not need to be Men of Courage and Strength, <hi>to be ſtrong in the Lord, and in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>the Power of his might;</hi> that ſo <hi>we may not be weary of well doing,</hi> but may perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in the Way of Holineſs, and hold out to the end, that we may be ſaved: Had we not need <hi>lay aſide every weight,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>and every Sin which do ſo eaſily beſet us, and run with Patience the Race that is ſet before us: Looking unto Jeſus, the Author and Finiſher of our Faith, who for the Joy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſs, and deſpiſed the ſhame, and now is ſet down at the Right Hand of the Throne of God.</hi> Therefore Chriſtian, the work we have to do, if we will keep on in Heavens way, and to finiſh our courſe with Joy, is to follow the Apoſtles Exhortation, <hi>To grow in Grace,</hi> and that is to be done <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 18.</note> two ways, <hi>Addendo &amp; Augendo. Firſt,</hi> By adding one Grace to another, <hi>Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diligence, to add to your Faith Vertue,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>and to Vertue Knowledge, and to Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Temperance, and to Temperance Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and to Patience Godlineſs, and to Godlineſs Brotherly-kindneſs, and to Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly-kindneſs
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40745:44"/> Charity. Secondly,</hi> By en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing every Grace we have, <hi>we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>you Brethren, that you encreaſe more and more.</hi> Let us get all the Grace we can, we may have need to uſe it all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we die: The Times may be ſuch, that weak Grace will not ſerve the turn, weak Grace will not be able to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtrong Temptations. It is ill truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a weak and tattered Ship, when the Seas are raging, and the Storms boyſterous. Weak Grace is next to no Grace, when Chriſt came to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in a great Storm, <hi>He ſaith to them,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Why are ye fearful, O ye of little Faith;</hi> where the ſame Story is related, Chriſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 4. 4.</note> ſaith to his Diſciples, <hi>Why are ye ſo fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> How is it that you have no Faith? Little Faith is next to no Faith. Let us labour therefore to be ſtrong Chriſtians: Let us labour to attain that meaſure of Faith, which <hi>Abraham</hi> had, that Patience which <hi>Job</hi> had, that Meckneſs which <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> had, that Chaſtity which <hi>Joſeph</hi> had, and that Courage and Zeal which <hi>Paul</hi> had: Let us labour after ſuch Faith as may remove Mountains (all the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Danger and Difficulty, which may occur to us in our Way) Faith whereby <hi>we may quench all the fiery Dart,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 16.</note>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:40745:44"/> 
                  <hi>of the Devil,</hi> whereby we may overcome the World, and our ſtrongeſt Luſts and Corruptions: Let us labour to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Patience too, let Patience have its perfect Work. The <hi>Greek</hi> Word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 4.</note> will teach us what the perfect work of Patience is; namely, to abide under any Affliction, as long as God will have it to lye upon us; if we can ſtrengthen theſe, and all other Graces, and become ſtrong Men in Chriſt, then we ſhall be able to overcome all the Difficulties of our Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and to get ſafe to Heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>It is very miſchievous when Fellow-Travellers fall out and quarrel by the Way, it makes their Journey very uncomfortable.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O That thoſe that are Fellow-Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers in the Way to Heaven, did walk together in that ſweet Union, and mutual Agreement, that I might be to ſeek for an Application of this Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: But alas, it is to be lamented with Tears of Blood (if poſſible) that this
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40745:45"/> is too applicable to them, though it be ſtrange as well as ſad that it ſhould be ſo. It is no wonder to ſee Lions, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and Bears to rent and tear one another, becauſe we know they are of a Savage Nature. It is no wonder to ſee ravenous Wolves to worry poor Sheep, becauſe that likewiſe is natural; but would it not be ſtrange to ſee the poor Sheep, which are harmleſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Creatures, to bite and worry one another: Even ſo we need not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſee the Seed of the Serpent, to have ſuch bitter Enmity againſt the Seed <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15.</note> of the Woman; to ſee thoſe <hi>that are born</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>after the Fleſh, to perſecute thoſe that are born after the Spirit;</hi> to ſee the Children of the Devil, to hate the Children of God: To ſee thoſe who are running to Hell, quarrel with thoſe that are going to Heaven: This is no new, this is no ſtrange thing; but to ſee thoſe who are walking in the ſame way, namely, of Holineſs; that are going to the ſame place, namely, to Heaven; who are Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the ſame Maſter, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lord Jeſus; who are Children of the ſame Father, <hi>viz.</hi> the Bleſſed God; who are of one Family, that is, the Family o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Faithful; who are Members of one
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40745:45"/> Body, that is, the Body of Chriſt; to ſee theſe ſtrive and contend, to ſee theſe full of Bitterneſs of Spirit one againſt another, of Envy, Emulations, Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Hatred; this is ſtrange, this is ſad,—<hi>Quis Talia fando—Temperet â Lachrimis.</hi> Can he that ſpeaks, or he that hears Such things as theſe, refrain from Tears?</p>
               <p>It is reported by Hiſtorians, that the <hi>Panther</hi> hath ſuch a hatred and enmity againſt Man, that if he ſee but the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of a Man, he will be inraged, and moſt fiercely and furiouſly fly at it, and tear it in Pieces: This is a lively Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of wicked Men, who have ſuch a perfect Hatred of Holineſs, which is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mage of God, that they are Inraged againſt all that bear that Image, and would not ſuffer one of them to live in the World, if they could have their Will. But methinks the Children of God, who are after God created in Righteouſneſs, and true Holineſs (or Holineſs of Truth, as in the Original) ſhould love this Image of God where-ever they find it, and ſhould ſay as one of the Ancients did, I cannot but love that Perſon in whom I ſee <hi>aliquid Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ti,</hi> any thing of Chriſt, but as it is ſaid
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40745:46"/> of carnal Brethren—<hi>Rara eſt concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia fratrum.</hi> 'Tis rare to ſee Brethren agree; ſo it may be ſaid (though it be very ſad it ſhould) of ſpiritual Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. We will now briefly examine the ground of this, whence it ſhould proceed, and propoſe ſome Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the Cure and Remedy of it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> For the Grounds of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> In general, Queſtionleſs, that Corruption which is in our Nature, is the cauſe of this, as well as of all other Sins; <hi>From whence comes Wars and fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>among you? come they not hence, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of your Luſts that War in your Members?</hi> Though Corruption in the Regenerate be in ſome Meaſure ſubdued; yet <hi>aliquid haerebit,</hi> there are remainders of it in the beſt, and we cannot be rid of this Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Death, till the Death of our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and therefore, where there is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in Opinions, there will be Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in Affection; but more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, there be theſe things which are the Ground and Cauſe of this Evil.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Pride and Self-conceit. <hi>He tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 25. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>is of a proud Heart, ſtirreth up Strife<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Only by Pride cometh Contention.</hi> If eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of us could hearken to that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Apoſtle, which is ſo elegant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:40745:46"/> ly expreſſed (which is thus rendred in our Tranſlation) <hi>Not to think of himſelf</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>more highly then he ought to think, but to think ſoberly:</hi> This would be one great means to cure and compoſe our Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences; for if every one had better Thoughts of all, and low Thoughts of himſelf, he would not ſo magiſterially impoſe his Conceptions upon others, and quarrel with every one that will not come up to his Model. If every one did as the Apoſtle exhorts, <hi>Eſteem o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers better than himſelf, nothing would be</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>done through ſtrife and vain-glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another cauſe is <hi>Paſſion. A</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>froward Man ſoweth Strife:</hi> Men of hot and fiery Spirits are apt to breed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and Quarrel in the Church, as well as in the State; whereas he that is of a meek and quiet Spirit, will be ſo far from kindling the Fire of Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Diviſions, that he will labour to quench the Flame that others have kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled. I am perſwaded, if <hi>Luther</hi> had been of <hi>Calvin's</hi> Spirit, Reformation of Religion had been carried on to a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er heighth, and that we had not had ſo great Rents and Diviſions in the Church as now we have.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Another cauſe of this Evil,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40745:47"/> is that which the Apoſtle blames in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> which cauſed Diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and that is the crying up of one Teacher, to the diſparagement and contempt of all others. <hi>I am of Paul, I am of Apollos, I am of Cephas;</hi> theſe were excellent Preachers, and as <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> the Apoſtle ſaith, in the end of the third Chapter, they were all theirs; and therefore they ought to have improved their ſeveral Gifts, for their ſpiritual Benefit and Advantage; and to have had them all in ſingular Love, for their Works ſake, and not by preferring of one, to forſake all the reſt: You may obſerve, that they who admire and are addicted to one Teacher, or one Party with undervaluing and ſlighting all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, are ſeldom the moſt profiting or the moſt profitable, but never the moſt peaceful Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I might add another ground of this Evil, and that is the Itch of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting, or that which the Apoſtle calls, <hi>Vain Jangling;</hi> of which, as one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 6.</note> well, <hi>Diſputandi pruritus Eccleſiae Scabies.</hi> The Itch of Diſputing is the Churches Scab; and I dare add, that it is the bane of Holy Conference, and the Spawn of Diſſenſion. The Apoſtle ſaith expreſly,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40745:47"/> that from this <hi>doting about Queſtions and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtrife of Words, cometh Envy, Strife, Railing, Evil-ſurmiſings:</hi> But I ſhall ſay no more of this, becauſe I conceive thoſe hot and eager Diſputes, which tend to Diviſions, ariſe either from Pride or Paſſion, which I have ſpoken of before; but modeſt, ſober, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble debating of Things neither ingender Strife, nor break the Peace. And now having diſcovered the Grounds and Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this Diſtemper, what a Happineſs would it be if we could preſcribe a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy? In order to this, I ſhall adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to give Chriſtians one Direction, and ſome few Conſiderations, which may by the Bleſſing of God be helpful to this purpoſe. The <hi>Direction</hi> is this, <hi>That Chriſtians would carefully ſhun and avoid thoſe things before ſpoken of, which are the chief Cauſes of Quarrels and Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions among the People of God;</hi> for <hi>ſublata cauſa tollitur effectus:</hi> Take away the Cauſe, and you take away the Effect. Take heed therefore of Pride, and of an over-weaning Opinion of thine Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities: Take heed of a Paſſionate, and of a froward Spirit: Take heed of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Mens Perſons in Admiration, or of Idolizing a Party: Take heed that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40745:48"/> thou delight not in wrangling and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting; if theſe things were carefully avoided, there would be more Peace and ſweet Agreement between true Chriſtians. But further, to promote the cure of this Diſtemper, I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Chriſtians in the fear of God, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly lay to Heart theſe following Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider, how highly it is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to the Bleſſed God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> To God the Father: It is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to an earthly Father to ſee his Children always brabbling and fighting each with other; and it muſt needs be more diſpleaſing to our Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who is the Father of Mercies, to ſee his Children unmerciful (who is the <hi>God of Love and Peace)</hi> to ſee his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren hating and quarrelling one with <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 11.</note> another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It muſt needs be diſpleaſing to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to ſee thoſe for whom he hath ſhed his Precious Blood, to be ready to ſhed one anothers Blood; to ſee the Members of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to rend and tear one another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It muſt needs <hi>grieve the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit of God,</hi> to ſee thoſe whom he <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 30.</note> hath ſanctified, thoſe whom he hath
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40745:48"/> ſealed for Heaven, to be ſo like grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Perſons, to fall out and quarrel by the Way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider, it is a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to our Holy Profeſſion: How did it Credit Religion, and adorn the Goſpel, <hi>When the Multitude of them that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>believed were of one Heart, and of one Soul?</hi> And when the Heathen could ſay, <hi>Ecce quomodo Chriſtiani mutuò ſe diligunt!</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold! how the Chriſtians love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. On the other ſide, what a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour and reproach is it to Religion, when the Profeſſors of it are quarrelling and contending one with the other? What Sport doth this make for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and Atheiſtical Men? And how doth it cauſe the Enemy to blaſpheme the Holy Ways of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider, How contrary this is to our Rule, and to our Pattern. A Chriſtian ſhould take Chriſt's Word for his Rule, and Chriſt's Example for his Pattern.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Firſt,</hi> How contrary is this quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling Frame of Spirit to our Rule? It is Chriſts new and great Command in the Goſpel, that his Diſciples <hi>ſhould</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 13. 34. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>love one another:</hi> And this is command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over and over, I know not how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40745:49"/> times in the New Teſtament: <hi>Be kindly affectioned one to another, with Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 22. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 13. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 9. <hi>Mark</hi> 9. 50. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Love, in Honour, preferring one to another. Love the Brotherhood: Love one another with a pure Heart fervently: Let Brotherly Love continue: By Love ſerve one another: You are taught of God to Love one another.</hi> And as our Rule injoyns us Love, ſo Peace and Quietneſs: <hi>Have Peace one with another: Let us follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe things which make for Peace, and things wherewith one may Edifie one another.</hi> The Apoſtle beſeecheth them, <hi>that they ſtudy to be quiet.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> tells <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 11.</note> them, <hi>That the Ornament of a meck and quiet Spirit, is in the ſight of God of great</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Price.</hi> So you ſee clearly, how contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it is to the Rules of the Goſpel, that Chriſtians ſhould be of a froward, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet and contentious Spirit? The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>If it be poſſible, as much as in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>you lies, live peaceably with all Men.</hi> And certainly, then much more ſhould we live peaceably with thoſe of the Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> How unlike doth a froward quarrelling Spirit, make Chriſtians to Chriſt. <hi>Learn of me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for I am</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>meek and lowly.</hi> Chriſt was the greateſt Pattern of Love and Meekneſs that ever
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:40745:49"/> was in the World, he was mild and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful to his Enemies, And ſhall we be harſh and ſevere to our Brethren? He loved his Sheep, ſo that he laid down his Life for them, and ſhall his Sheep (as if they were turned Dogs) bait and bite one another? Such a Member of ſuch a Head make Rents and Diviſions in his Body, which is the Church of God; ſhould thoſe who are the Subjects of the Prince of Peace, make Wars and Feuds among themſelves?</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>—Pudet haec opprobria nobis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe refelli.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>What Shame is it, that ſuch diſgrace ſhould be imputed to us, and that it cannot be refuted?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Conſider the danger of this unnatural quarrel: <hi>If ye bite and devour</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>one another, take heed that ye be not conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of one another.</hi> Are not the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of thoſe that profeſs Religion the ready way to betray both themſelves and the Cauſe of God into the Hands of thoſe who wait for their Deſtruction: How juſtly may God give us up into the Hands of thoſe that hate us, if we hate one another? Doth not a Father part
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40745:50"/> his fighting Children with a Rod?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Conſider, That Love to the Brethren, is one of the cleareſt Marks and Characters of a Regenerate Perſon in the whole Bible; and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, want of Love to the Brethren, is made an evident Sign of want of Love to God. <hi>By this ſhall all Men know, that you are my Diſciples, if you Love one</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>another. We know that we have paſſed from Death to Life, becauſe we love the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Brethren.</hi> And for the other ſee, <hi>He that hates his Brother is in darkneſs. If a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 9. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Man ſaith, I Love God and hate his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he is a Liar, for he that loveth not his Brother whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God whom he hath not ſeen.</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks this ſhould be enough to fright the Children of God from Variance and Diſagreement; for what is there, that a Gracious Heart is more ſollicitous and careful about than this, to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be in a ſtate of Grace or no?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Conſider, We have Enemies enough, and therefore we need not be Enemies among our ſelves; All the World hate us, and therefore we ſhould not hate one another. If a Company of Chriſtians ſhould live among the <hi>Turks</hi> or among <hi>Cannibals,</hi> would it not be
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40745:50"/> their Wiſdom, and their Safety to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and combine together; would they not dread private Diſſenſions and Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences among themſelves, leaſt it ſhould betray them to the common Enemy? Why ſo it is with all real Chriſtians: They live in the midſt of Enemies, nay of <hi>Cannibals,</hi> who would eat them up like Bread; and therefore it concerns them not to quarrel and fall out among themſelves, leaſt it fare with them as with the <hi>Mouſe</hi> and the <hi>Frog</hi> in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Methinks Chriſtians ſhould learn Wiſdom from their Enemies, <hi>Fas eſt ab boſte doceri.</hi> How well do the wicked agree in their evil Practices, and in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the Righteous? <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> were ſoon made Friends.</p>
               <lg>
                  <head>Sevis inter ſe convenit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſis.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Bears as Savage as they be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet do among themſelves agree.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Now ſhall the Bears and Savage Beaſts agree with thoſe of their own Kind, and ſhall thoſe that are walking on in the Broad-way to Deſtruction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together? and ſhall thoſe that are going in the way that leads to Heaven
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40745:51"/> and Happineſs diſagree, and fall out by the Way? <hi>Tell it not in Gath, publiſh it</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>not in the Streets of Askalon, leaſt the Daughters of the Philiſtines rejoyce, leaſt the Daughters of the uncircumciſed Triumph.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly</hi> and Laſtly, Conſider What an irrational and abſurd thing it is, that leſſer Differences in Opinion which are between the Children of God (when they agree in neceſſary and fundamental Truths) ſhould breed an Alienation and Eſtrangement in Affection? Were it not Madneſs for me to quarrel with every one whoſe Shooe will not fit my Foot? We may as well expect that all mens Faces ſhould be diſtinguiſhed from another, as that their Conceptions and Opinions ſhould be the ſame. Methinks when we know that we cannot be of one Mind, while we are in our Way, but that, that Happy State is reſerved for us, till we come to our Journeys end to Heaven. Methinks I ſay, this ſhould cauſe us to bear with thoſe that differ from us in leſſer Matters, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear cenſuring of them, much more to abſtain from quarrelling and contending with them. Alas! we differ from our ſelves from what we were heretofore,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40745:51"/> and therefore ſhall we quarrel with our ſelves? O now that theſe and ſuch like Conſiderations might make the Children of God to hearken to that ſweet Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Apoſtle! <hi>Put on therefore as</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 12, 13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>the Elect of God, Bowels of Mercies, Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Humbleneſs of Mind, Meekneſs, Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering, Forbearing one another, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving one another. If any Man have a quarrel againſt any, even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo do ye.</hi> O let us who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs our ſelves to be Children of God, and to be travelling to one Heaven, think that we heard our Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaying to us, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſaid to his Brethren! <hi>See that you fall not out by the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 45. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Way;</hi> or as <hi>Moſes</hi> to the two ſtriving <hi>Iſraelites; Sirs, You are Brethren, Why do ye wrong one another?</hi> And let us ſay <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 26.</note> one to another, <hi>As Abraham ſaid to Lot,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 13. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Let there be no ſtrife, I pray thee, between me and thee, for we are Brethren. Let us la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace.</hi> And let all the Strife and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention between us be, who ſhall be the moſt Holy, Humble, Heavenly-minded, Self-denying and Charitable Chriſtian; who ſhall ſerve God beſt, and love one another moſt; and then ſhall we walk on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hearfully and comfortably, till we come
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40745:52"/> to Heaven where all our Differences ſhall be at an end. For there <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> are agreed, there the Bleſſed God and all his Saints and Angels are of one Mind. Read the <hi>133d. Pſalm</hi> and heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to thoſe Pathetical Exhortations of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul. Now I beſeech you</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Brethren by the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no Diviſions among you, but that ye be perfectly joyned together in the ſame Mind, and in the ſame Judgment. If there be therefore any Conſolation in Chriſt, if any Comfort of Love, if any Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Spirit, if any Bowels and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Let nothing be done through Strife, or Vain Glory, but in lowlineſs of Mind, let each eſteem other better than themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>A Traveller who carrieth Treaſure with him, and ſuſpects that he may meet with Thieves, will go well Armed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Application of this Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will conſiſt of three Parts.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:40745:52"/>
                  <item> 1. To ſhew that the Heavenly Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller carries precious Treaſure with him.</item>
                  <item>2. That he will be ſet upon in his Way, by thoſe that will endeavour to Rob him of it.</item>
                  <item>3. That therefore he ſhould be well Arm'd.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> A Chriſtian in his Way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, carries the Richeſt Treaſure with him in all the World. 1. He carries his <hi>God</hi> with him, who is the <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> the chief Good in Compariſon of whom all the World is not ſo much as the drop of the Bucket to the Ocean, or the ſmall Duſt of the Ballance to the Univerſe. So thought the Bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul, Who counted all things, but loſs</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>and dung in Compariſon of Chriſt.</hi> So thought the <hi>Noble Marqueſs of</hi> Vico, as appears by that Holy and Heavenly ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his, <hi>Curſed be he that thinks not one Hours Communion with God, is not better then all the Money in the World.</hi> No! eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Saint of God may ſay, what one of them once did, <hi>Whether ever I go, I</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Quocunque me confero Deum cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumfero.</note> 
                  <hi>carry my God with me,</hi> and is not this an Infinite and invaluable Treaſure? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. He hath another precious Treaſure, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar more precious then Gold that periſheth,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 7.</note>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:40745:53"/> and that is <hi>Grace,</hi> to be rich in Grace is another manner of thing, then to be rich in Gold. <hi>The Riches of this World are</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>called uncertain Riches,</hi> and we find them to be ſo; but Grace is called durable Riches, and it is ſo; for he that hath <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 18.</note> this Treaſure on Earth, ſhall be ſure to have Treaſure in Heaven for ever more. 3. A Chriſtian hath another precious Jewel to ſecure in his Journey, and that is his <hi>Immortal Soul,</hi> and this alone (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven one Soul) is better then all the World, ſo our bleſſed Saviour tells us, who knew the worth of Souls, and paid a dear rate for them. <hi>What is a Man profited, if he ſhall gain the whole World</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>and loſe his own Soul, and what ſhall a Man give in exchange for his Soul?</hi> So thou ſeeſt Chriſtian, that thou carrieſt a rich Treaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> There be ſome that lie in wait for thee in thy way, and will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to rob thee of all this rich Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, of thy God, of thy Grace, of thy Soul: I gave thee warning before; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſixth Chapter, to take heed of three Arch-Seducers, and they were Satan, thine own Luſts, and the World Now theſe are the Thieves that will way-lay thee, and there endeavour to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40745:53"/> lead thee out of thy Way, as in order to the robbing thee of thy Rich Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; as High-way-men lead Travellers aſide out of the Road into ſome bye Lane, or Wood, where they may Rifle them of their Goods. Satan is an Old and Arch Thief, the other are Setters that will betray thee into his Hands; as the Hoſtler and Chamberlain many Times betray the Traveller, whom they find to carry good ſtore of Money, into the Hands of Thieves. Now thou canſt not be too careful of the World, and thy Luſts, leaſt they betray thee; nor too careful of Satan, leaſt he rob and ſpoil thee; he is the moſt dangerous Thief in the World; he laies wait for thee from the very firſt ſtep thou takeſt in thy Way, to the end of thy Journey; and he is a bloody Thief, he never Robs, but he murders; yea, and it is the worſt Murder too, for he Murders the Soul. So now Chriſtian, thou ſeeſt that tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> art like the Traveller who is richly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and thou wilt ſurely be ſet upon in thy Way; and therefore,</p>
               <p>In the Third Place, Thou muſt imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Travellers Wiſdom, and go well Armed: I think there is none, who hath underſtanding of Spiritual Things but is
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40745:54"/> convinced, that he who is Travelling for Heaven, hath more need to be well armed, then he that is Travelling on Earth; in as much, as he hath far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Riches to ſecure, and is like to meet with more dangerous Enemies and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailants. The Earthly Traveller is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or never robb'd upon the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of all he hath, becauſe he cannot carry his Lands and Livings, his Houſe, and Goods with him; and there, though he may loſe ſome or all his Money, yet he hath ſomething left him: But Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, thou maiſt ſay with <hi>Bias, Omnia mea mecum porto.</hi> If Satan rob thee of thy Soul, thou art undone: Thy all is gone, and thou maiſt lye in the dark Dungeon of Hell without a drop of Cold Water for ever. Tell me then, hadſt thou not need to look to thy ſelf, and go well armed againſt this Danger? I ſhall therefore inform thee, where thou maiſt have Armour of Proof; where there is a Magazine that will furniſh thee compleatly, <hi>Cap-a-pe, a Capite a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> calicem,</hi> and is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The whole Armour of God, ſtand therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving your Loins girt about with Truth, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>having on the Breaſt-Plate of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Taking the Shield of Faith, whereby
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:40745:54"/> you ſhall be able to quench all the fiery Darts of the Wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d; and take the Helmet of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and the Sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God;</hi> and to all theſe, thou muſt add Prayer; <hi>Praying always with all Prayer and Supplication in the Spirit:</hi> Here <note place="margin">
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 18.</note> is compleat Armour, which hath put Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to flight many a Time. But it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, here is no one piece for the Back, to ſhew that a Chriſtian muſt be armed with Courage, as well as with Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and muſt never turn his Back: If thou doſt not turn thy Back upon Satan, Satan will turn his Back upon thee; <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Devil, and he will fly from thee.</hi> Now if thou wouldſt know how to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 7.</note> Weild this Spiritual Armour, and how to uſe every Piece of it ſucceſsfully. Read Mr. <hi>William Gurnal</hi> his <hi>Chriſtian in Compleat Armour,</hi> or Doctor <hi>Arrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith</hi> his <hi>Tactica Sacra.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:40745:55"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>He that Travelleth with a ſtrong Guard needs not fear being robbed or hindered in his Journey.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>EVery Child of God is ſo ſtrongly Guarded, that he needs not fear all the Powers of Earth or Hell; neither Hoſts of Men, nor Armies of Devils: And they whoſe Eyes are opened by Faith, to ſee this as the Prophets Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants was, to ſee <hi>The Mountain full of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Horſes of Fire, and Chariots of Fire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ound about his Maſter,</hi> will ſay, <hi>That they that be with us, are more then they that be with them. David</hi> could ſee this, for what elſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould make him ſay, <hi>I will not be</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>afraid of ten thouſand of People, that have ſet themſelves againſt me round about. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> will not fear, what Man can do unto me.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Though I walk through the Valley of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhadow of Death, yet I will fear no Evil</hi> But I will ſhew thee, what Guard every Child of God hath to keep him ſafe til<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he come to Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> They have a <hi>Guard of Angels
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:40745:55"/> He hath given his Angels charge over thee</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>to keep thee in all thy Ways.</hi> If thou keep thy Way, the Angels ſhall keep thee; but if thou goeſt out of thy Way, thou canſt not lay claim to this Promiſe: See again, <hi>Are they not all miniſtring Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, ſent forth to Miniſter for them, who</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall be Heirs of Salvation. The Angel of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord encampeth round about them that fear him, and delivereth them. Behold, I</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>ſend an Angel before thee, to keep thee in the Way, and to bring thee to the Place that I have prepared.</hi> Now what a ſtrong Guard is this, If we conſider, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Their Power. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Their Number.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider their Power, they are ſaid, <hi>to excel in Power:</hi> They are <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 7.</note> called <hi>mighty Angels,</hi> and well they may; for we read, that one Angel went out and ſlew eighty five thouſand in the Camp of the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> in one Night. <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. 35.</note> And I doubt not, but one ſingle Angel, if the Lord ſhould give him Commiſſion, could eaſily ſmite all the World, and make them all Dead Men: So that you ſee, if we had but one Angel to Guard us, while we are Travelling through the Wilderneſs of this World to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Canaan,</hi> we ſhould be ſtrongly guarded. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:40745:56"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> How ſtrong is this Guard, if you conſider the number of Angels; if there be ſo much ſtrength in one An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, what is there in an Hoſt of Angels? <hi>Jacob</hi> calls them Gods Hoſt, <hi>Jacob went on his Way, and the Angels of God met</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. 1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>him, and when Jacob ſaw them, he ſaid, This is Gods Hoſt,</hi> and they make a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Hoſt; <hi>I heard the Voice of many Angels. The Chariots of the Lord are</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>twenty Thouſand, even Thouſands of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> Our Saviour ſaith, he could have <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 23.</note> prayed to his Father and ſhould have given him more then twelve Legions of Angels: If this be not enough the Apoſtle tells us, that there be an <hi>innumerable</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Company of Angels:</hi> So now we ſee that every true Chriſtian hath a ſtrong <hi>Life-Guard,</hi> when all the Angels that excel in might, and exceed in number are charged by the Great Commander of Heaven and Earth to Miniſter to them: but they have a ſtronger Guard yet, for</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Not only the Angels of God, but alſo the <hi>God of Angels</hi> is their keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>Behold, he that keepeth Iſrael, ſhall</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121. 4, <hi>to</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>neither ſlumber nor ſleep. The Lord is thy keeper, the Lord is thy ſhade upon thy right Hand. The Lord ſhall preſerve thee from
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:40745:56"/> all Evil.</hi> We read, that the Lords Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. 26, 27.</note> is his People, and that he keeps them as the Apple of his Eye (and ſurely then they muſt be well kept) the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 30. 9.</note> Lord will Guard them before and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and round about, and then who can hurt them? he will be their Vant-Guard, <hi>The Lord your God which goeth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 1. 30. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>before you, he ſhall fight for you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For ye ſhall not go out with haſte, nor go by flight, for the Lord will go before them, and the God of Iſrael will be your Rere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. As the Mountains are round about Jeruſalem, ſo the Lord is round about his</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125. 2</note> 
                  <hi>People from henceforth, even for ever:</hi> So it is clear, that the Lord will Guard his People. In the next Place, that he is a ſtrong Guard, I cannot think any arrived at the heighth of Atheiſm and Impudence, as to deny it; for if he was Impotent, nay, if he were not Potent, he could not be God: But I am ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſtians, who will be ſatisfied with Scripture. <hi>In the Lord Jehovah is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 4. <hi>Job</hi> 9. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Everlaſting Strength: If I ſpeak of St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ength he is ſtrong.</hi> Our Saviour uſeth this as an Argument why his Sheep ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver periſh, <hi>My Father which gave them me is ſtronger than all, and none is able to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>pluck them out of my Fathers Hand.</hi> I
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:40745:57"/> could produce many more Scriptures, as <hi>Pſalm</hi> 24. 8. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 89. 8. but I need not multiply Texts to prove ſo plain a Truth; I ſhall only mention one more. <hi>Behold all the Nations of the Earth are as</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>the drop of a Bucket, and are accounted as the ſmall Duſt of the Ballance.</hi> But this doth not ſufficiently ſet forth the Power of the Omnipotent; therefore it is ſaid, <hi>All the Nations before him are as nothing,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>ver.</hi> 17.</note> but this doth not reach it neither, and therefore it follows, <hi>they are counted to be leſs then nothing and Vanity.</hi> So you ſee what his Word ſaith, but we may further conſider his Infinite Power by his Works. He is the great God who made Heaven <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.</note> and Earth out of nothing, who ſhaketh the Earth out of her Place; <hi>And the Mountains melt before him: Who hath ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered the Wind in his Fiſt? Who hath mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Judg.</hi> 5. 5. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>the Waters in the hollow of his Hand, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>meted out the Heavens with a Span, and comprehended the Duſt of the Earth in a Meaſure, and weighed the Mountains in Scales, and the Hills in a Ballance.</hi> The Sea retreats at his Command, <hi>and the Rock becomes a ſtanding Water, and the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 114. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Flint a Fountain. The Pillars of Heaven tremble, and are aſtoniſhed at his Reproof;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 26. 11</note> and Hell is naked before him. <hi>Lo, theſe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:40745:57"/> are the Parts of his Ways, but how little a Portion is heard of him? But the Thunder of his Power, who can underſtand?</hi> Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der further, what Acts of his Power God hath put forth from Time to Time for the Safety and Preſervation of his People; He hath reſtrained the Fire from Burning, and the Water from <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14. 21. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 22.</note> Drowning, and the Hungry Lions from Devouring them: He hath put a Hook into the Noſtrils of the moſt inraged Enemies, hath reproved Kings for their ſake; yea, for their ſake, <hi>He ſmote great</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136. 17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Kings, and ſlew famous Kings.</hi> And laſtly, He hath reſerved their greateſt Enemies the Devils <hi>in Chains to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Great Day.</hi> Behold! what <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jude</hi> 6.</note> ſafety have all the Saints, who have this God to be their <hi>Lord Protector?</hi> He can raiſe all the <hi>Poſſe</hi> of Heaven and Earth, for the ſafe Conduct of thoſe who are Travelling to his Kingdom; but if he Arm the leaſt and moſt contemptible Creatures, they ſhall be ſtrong enough to ſecure them, and deſtroy their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries. By this Time, I hope thou art ſatisfied, that the Children of God are well Guarded in their Journey to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, and therefore it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low clearly, that they need not fear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:40745:58"/> hindred in their Way, nor robbed of their Treaſure: What God ſaith to <hi>Abraham,</hi> he ſaith to all who are Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Abraham, Fear not, I am thy Shield.</hi> Sure he muſt needs be ſafe, who is <hi>ſub Omnipotentis clypeo,</hi> under the Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the Almighty. Well then Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, go on thy Way with Courage and Chearfulneſs: What is it that thou Feareſt? Is it Satan? Why, the Lord ſhall trample him under thy Feet ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>for the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>againſt any of his:</hi> Doſt thou fear Men, the Lord is on thy ſide, what can Fleſh do unto thee? Thy Protector can look all thy Enemies into Confuſion, as he did Proud <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his Hoſt, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exo.</hi> 14. 24.</note> them with the Breath of his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils: Do thou keep on in Heavens way, and all the Power of Earth and Hell ſhall never be able to keep thee out of Heaven, For the Lord ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve thee, <hi>by his Power through Faith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:40745:58"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>Though the Traveller find good En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment at his Inn, yet he takes not up his abode there, but is Reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, till he come to his own Home.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Wiſe Chriſtian looks upon this World as his Inn, and takes it but <hi>in tranſitu</hi> in his Way to a better World. He doth not ſay, <hi>It is good to be here,</hi> Let us build Tabernacles, but <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. 4.</note> he uſeth the World as if he uſed it not: If God giveth him Riches, a plentiful Eſtate, a convenient Habitation, kind Relations, he bleſſeth God and ſaith, <hi>This is a good Inn:</hi> But this is not my Home, this is not my Heaven. I deſire to be thankful that I find ſo good En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment in my Way, but I look for better at my Journeys End. I have cauſe to bleſs God, that I meet with ſo fair Quarter here where I am a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; but I expect far better when I come to my Home, and to my Fathers Houſe, and therefore I long to be there. When a Traveller comes to his Inn,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40745:59"/> though he like his Chamber very well, yet he doth not ſend for rich Tapeſtry and Hangings, and other Ornaments to furniſh and adorn it; for he conſiders that he is to lodge there but one Night, and then muſt reſign it to another. So a Saint of God, who is a Citizen of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, though he may enjoy comfortable Accommodations here on Earth; yet he looks upon them all as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch as he muſt ſhortly part with and leave to others, and therefore endeavours that his Heart may ſit looſe from them. If he hath a goodly Houſe on Earth, he knows he muſt ſhortly be turned out of it; and therefore he looks out for a Houſe, <hi>not made with Hands, Eternal in the Heavens,</hi> and for a Manſion which Chriſt is gone to prepare for him; and though he hath <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>John</hi> 14. 12.</note> a very fair earthly Inheritance, yet he knows he is but a Tenant at will, and therefore he looks for a Heavenly, <hi>For</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>an Inheritance incorruptible, undefiled, that fadeth not away, reſerved in Heaven for him.</hi> If he be as Rich as <hi>Solomon</hi> was, yet he knows that theſe are uncertain Riches, and will ſoon take Wings and be gone; and therefore he looks after durable Riches, and Treaſures in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>which no Ruſt can corrupt no Thieves</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 17.</note>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:40745:59"/> 
                  <hi>rob them of:</hi> Though he hath Dear Friends and Relations on Earth, yet he <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 20.</note> knows he hath better Friends and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Heaven; and upon theſe Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, he uſeth the World but as a thorough-Fare, <hi>and ſeeks for a better Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try even a Heavenly.</hi> But how is it with <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 16.</note> the greater Part of Men? Do they uſe the World as if they uſed it not? Do they uſe it as a Traveller doth his Inn? Surely no, but they uſe it as a ſottiſh Drunkard doth the Ale-houſe, where you may find them Day and Night, where they ſpend all their Time and all their Subſtance too. Alas! moſt Men make the World their Home, their Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, their Heaven, their God. This World hath all their Hearts, all their Thoughts, all their Care, all their Time, all their Affections. In the mean Time, God, Heaven, and their immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Souls are wholly neglected, <hi>God is not in all their Thoughts;</hi> the Children of God make them Friends of the unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Mammon, but the Children of this World make Mammon their God. When the Rich Fools Wealth and Corn came flowing in upon him, he takes up his Reſt in them: <hi>Soul,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Take thine Eaſe, thou haſt Goods laid up for</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 12.</note>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:40745:60"/> 
                  <hi>many Years.</hi> But when God had eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed good <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> in the Kingdom, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18. 1. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17. 6.</note> and bleſſed him with Riches and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in abundance, his Heart was not lifted up with theſe things, but his Heart was lifted up in the Ways of the Lord. A real Chriſtian ſhould uſe all the Comforts and Enjoyments of this World, as they may be helps and not hinderances to him in his Way to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter World. He ſaith with <hi>Luther, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo ſic ſatiari,</hi> I will not be ſo ſatisfied, I will not be put off with theſe things; and with <hi>Auſtin, Domine nolo omnia quae dediſti, niſi das teipſum qui dediſti omnia.</hi> Lord, I will not be content with all that thou haſt given me, unleſs thou giveſt me thy ſelf, who haſt given me all. His Soul is unſatisfied with all his earthly Enjoyments, and he is reſtleſs till he comes to Heaven which he counts his Home, to the immediate and Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Enjoyment of God in Glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:40745:60"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>Many a Traveller hath been ready to faint in his Way, and to fear that he ſhould never reach his Journeys end, who yet hath attained it with Safety.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Chapter is very applicable to a Chriſtian in his Journey to Heaven in both the Parts of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Is not he ſubject to fainting fits while he is in his Earthly Pilgrimage? Is he not full of Doubts and Fears, that he ſhall never hold out to the End? Doth he not ſometimes fear leaſt his <hi>evil Heart of unbelief,</hi> will cauſe him <hi>to depart from</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>the Living God,</hi> leaſt a Promiſe being made of entring into Reſt, he ſhould <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 5.</note> come ſhort of it? Sometimes his Luſts and Corruptions are ſo impetuous and violent, that he cries out, <hi>Theſe Sons of Zerviah will be too hard for me!</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Devil purſues him with ſuch hideous Temptations and Helliſh Inje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that he ſaith in his Heart; <hi>I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one Day periſh by the Hand of Satan.</hi> Sometime he is under Spiritual Deſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:40745:61"/> he ſits in Darkneſs and ſees no Light: He hath no Senſe nor feeling of the Love and Favour of God, and then his Heart fails him; and then he ſaith with <hi>Jonah, I am caſt out of thy ſight;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jonah</hi> 2. 4.</note> and in this Condition he is ſo far from being Confident that he ſhall attain the end of his Journey, that he fears he was never yet in his right Way, he calls all in Queſtion, and thinks that his Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and turning from Sin proceeded only from legal Terrours, and from the Conviction of a natural Conſcience, and not from the Work of ſaving Grace: He bears falſe Witneſs againſt himſelf, and makes deſperate Concluſions, that he is a Hypocrite, a Caſt-a-way; one of the Fooliſh Virgins that ſhall be ſhut out of Heaven for ever: And this I think doth plainly prove the firſt Point, that a Chriſtian is apt to be ſurprized with fainting in his Way towards Heaven, and to fear that he ſhall never attain his Journeys End. Theſe things may ſeem Riddles and Paradoxes to the Mad World, and may be to them matter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Scorn and Deriſion, but thoſe who ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> acquainted with the Ways of God, and with the Method of his carrying on the Work of Grace upon the Hearts of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:40745:61"/> People do know that theſe are experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Truths.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> Though a Child of God be in this Condition, though he ſeem to deſpair that ever he ſhall hold out till he comes to Heaven, Yet he ſhall aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly attain it with Safety and Comfort. <hi>David</hi> ſaid in his Heart (and we may ſay in haſte too) <hi>I ſhall one Day periſh by the Hands of Saul,</hi> but we know he did not; nay, indeed he could not, for the faithful God had promiſed, that he ſhould ſucceed <hi>Saul</hi> in the Kingdom. So many a precious Saint of God thinks in his Heart, that he ſhall ſometime or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be foiled and turned out of the way by Satan, and by his own Corruptions, and ſo periſh for ever, but he ſhall not for all that; nay he cannot, for though he ſeems to let go his hold of God, yet God will not let go his hold of him, for he hath ſaid, <hi>I will never, never, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 5. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>leave thee, nor forſake thee. And the Election of God ſtandeth ſure, having this Seal, for the Lord knoweth who are his.</hi> And the Lord Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Of all that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 17. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>thou haſt given me, I have loſt none.</hi> Tho the Righteous <hi>ſcarcely</hi> be ſaved, yet they ſhall <hi>ſurely</hi> be ſaved; though with much <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 18.</note> difficulty, yet with all certainty: Tho'
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:40745:62"/> a Chriſtians Condition be ſometimes Dark and Cloudy; yet <hi>the Sun of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall ariſe upon them with healing under his Wings. Though his Fleſh and his Heart fail, yet God will be the Strength</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>of his Heart, and his Portion for ever;</hi> though he ſeem to faint in the Way, yet the Almighty will renew his Strength, and will make him to hold out to the End and be Saved. That is a ſweet Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 31. <hi>They that wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord ſhall renew their Strength, they ſhall mount up with Wings as Eagles, they ſhall run and not be weary, they ſhall walk and not faint:</hi> How full of Spiritual and Heavenly Conſolation is this one Word of God? Let us (Fellow-Travellers) carry this as a Soveraign Cordial with us in our Heavenly Journey, and it will revive our Drooping Spirits, when we are ready to faint, and will put Strength and Courage into us, to go on chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of our Way, till we come to Heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:40745:62"/>
               <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>When a Traveller after a long and dangerous Journey returns Home in Safety, how will his Father em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him? How will all his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions welcome him? What mutual Joy and Rejoycing will there be?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CHriſtian, If my Tongue were the Tongue of the Learned, or as the Pen of a ready Writer, if I were as eloquent as <hi>Apollos,</hi> if I had been wrapt up into the Third <hi>Heaven,</hi> and into Paradiſe with <hi>Paul.</hi> Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I were no way able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs that tranſcendent Joy and Happineſs which thou and all thy Fellow Creatures, who (taking the Spirit of God for your Guide, and his Word for your Rule) have walked in his Ways, and perſevered therein to the End, ſhall enjoy, when you have finiſhed your Courſe, when you have <hi>fought the good fight,</hi> when your warfare is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed. <hi>Paul</hi> who had a ſight or glimpſe of it, could not utter what he heard and ſaw, he ſaith, he heard <hi>unſpeakable Words,</hi> and doubtleſs he ſaw <hi>unſpeakable Joies,</hi> ſuch as cannot be uttered; yet that thou maiſt be encouraged to keep on thy way againſt all Oppoſition and Diſcouragements, I ſhall endeavour <hi>(pro mea tenuitate)</hi> to give thee a little taſt of what Entertainment thou wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meet with at thy Journeys End, and how thou wilt be welcomed into Heaven.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:40745:63"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Firſt, The Bleſſed God,</hi> thy Heavenly Father will bid thee welcome into his Kingdom, as the Prodigals Father did him to his Houſe, <hi>Who ran</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 15. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>to meet him and fell on his Neck and kiſſed him,</hi> and expreſſed all the Tokens of his Joy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joicing at his return. I know that Parable is a lively Repreſentation of our Heavenly Fathers entertaining a Penitent Sinner at his firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion: But if he ſo welcome a Sinner into the Kingdom of his Grace, how will he welcome a Saint into his Kingdom of Glory? Our Saviour tells us, <hi>It is your Fathers good Pleaſure to give</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>you the Kingdom;</hi> and if he be well pleaſed to give us the Kingdom, ſurely he cannot but be well pleaſed to give us the Poſſeſſion of the Kingdom. If he hath prepared a Kingdom for <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 34.</note> us from the Foundation of the World, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but rejoice to ſee us inherit that Kingdom. And as thy Heavenly Father will be delighted to ſee thee ſo, How will thy Soul be raviſhed with the Beatifical Viſion of thy God? If to ſee but his Back Parts here, and to ſee him but darkly in the Glaſs of Ordinances, be far the ſweeteſt Enjoyment, that ever thy Soul taſted on Earth? O think and admire, what it will be to ſee him <hi>as he is,</hi> and to be made like unto <note place="margin">1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 2.</note> him in Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> How will <hi>Chriſt thy Elder Brother</hi> welcome thee with an <hi>Euge bone Serve? Well done, good and faithful Servant, enter thou into</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>the Joy of thy Lord. Come thou Bleſſed of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inherit the Kingdom.</hi> Thou haſt ſuffered with me, and thou ſhalt reign now with me: Thou haſt born my Croſs and thou ſhalt wear my Crown: How will Chriſt rejoice to ſee thoſe that were the purchaſe of his own Blood, to be ſo advanced and to be where he is, when
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:40745:63"/> 
                  <hi>he ſhall thus ſee the Travel of his Soul, How will he be ſatisfied?</hi> And then Chriſtian, what Joy and Rejoycing will it be to thy Soul to ſee thy Bleſſed Saviour (who was Crucified and Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Thornes for thy ſake) to be Crowned with Glory, and ſitting with his Father on his Throne, and attended with Thouſands of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Angels and Glorified Saints?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> How will the <hi>Glorious Angels</hi> meet thee with <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Jubilation.</hi> Certainly, if there be Joy in the Preſence of the Angels of God over one Sinner that repents, there will be great Joy over every Saint that is glorified? How will they rejoice to ſee thoſe whom they had charge to keep in all their Ways, to come ſafe to Heaven, and to be entred into their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and to increaſe their <hi>Chorus,</hi> and to joyn with them in their Hallelujahs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> With what Joy will the <hi>Saints</hi> meet and embrace? How will <hi>Abraham</hi> receive thee into his Boſom? How will all thy Fellow-Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers and Fellow-Sufferers, all the Patriarchs, Prophets, Apoſtles, and Martyrs, and Saints of the Lord Jeſus welcome thee to thine Eternal Reſt? And how will it fill thy Soul with ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing Joy to think that theſe ſhall be thy Companions for ever? If the Society of the Saints on Earth was ſo delightful, when they were ſo full of Corruption and Infirmities? What will it be in Heaven, where the Spirits of Juſt Men ſhall be made perfect, not having ſpot or wrinkle or any ſuch thing, but they ſhall be Holy and without blemiſh?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The <hi>Place</hi> where thou ſhalt arrive at thy Journeys end, and where thou ſhalt take up thine <hi>Everlaſting abode,</hi> muſt needs affect thee with admirable Delight. We have a Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:40745:64"/> of a City, <hi>The Foundations of whoſe Walls</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.</note> 
                  <hi>were laid with all manner of precious Stones, the Twelve Gates, of Twelve intire Pearls, the Streets of the City Paved with pure Gold, as it were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Glaſs.</hi> I am not ignorant that ſome Learned Men have interpreted this of a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Church upon Earth; but Mr. <hi>Brightman,</hi> who is of that Opinion, ſaith, <hi>Complures inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretantur haec omnia de Eccleſia, qualis eſt futura tandem in Coelis.</hi> That very many interpret this of the Church as it ſhall be in Heaven, We need not contend, contrary Interpreters are in the right: For if the Church on Earth ſhall be ſo glorious, queſtionleſs it ſhall be much more glorious in Heaven; and let the Interpretation of that City be what it will, certainly the Court and chief Place of Reſidence of the great King of Heaven and Earth, muſt needs be a Place of unſpeakable Glory: And though that City be ſet out under the higheſt Repreſentations that can be borrowed from natural Things, yet it comes as far ſhort of the Glory of Heaven, as a Town of Mud-walls and Thatch comes ſhort of ſuch a City. How glorious muſt the inſide of that Cabinet be, where the outſide is Enamel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſo many bright and glittering Stars? And how glorious wilt thou be, when thou haſt all theſe under thy Feet? And when the great Ones of the Earth ſhall go from their ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly Palaces, even where they did ſurfeit with all Earthly Delights and Senſual Pleaſures into a dark Hell, where they cannot have a drop of Cold Water: O what a miſerable change will this be! And how will it fill them with horrour and deſpair? But when a poor Child of God ſhall go from this Valley of Tears (where he hath been afflicted, deſpiſed and perſecuted,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:40745:64"/> into a glorious Heaven, where he ſhall enjoy Everlaſting Reſt and Bleſſedneſs. O what a happy Change will this be! And how muſt he needs be tranſported with Joy unſpeakable and full of Glory? So now I have ſhewed thee (Chriſtian) what Happineſs thou (and all that walk in the Way of Holineſs) ſhall enjoy when you are come to your Journeys End, namely, all thoſe glorious Priviledges which the Apoſtle ſaith the Church ſhall enjoy under the Goſpel. <hi>You are come to the City of the Living God, to the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 22, 23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Heavenly Jeruſalem, and to an innumerable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Angels, to the general Aſſembly and Church of the firſt-born, which are Written in Heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the Spirits of Just Men made perfect, and to Jeſus the Mediator of the New Covenant.</hi> Now though this be enough to make thy Eſtate unſpeakably Happy and Joyful; yet there be many other things which thou wilt meet with in Heaven, which will make it full meaſure, preſſed down, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning over; As</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> How many Dangers and Difficulties a gracious God hath brought thee through. <hi>Quod fuit durum puti meminiſſe dulce eſt:</hi> It is pleaſant to a Traveller when he hath overcome his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to relate what Dangers he hath met with in his Way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That thou haſt overcome all thy Doubts and Fears, for when thou art in Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Enjoyment, how canſt thou any more Doubt or Fear?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That thou art freed from all Satans Temptations, for though he got into the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Paradiſe, yet he ſhall never come into the Heavenly; <hi>For there ſhall in no wiſe come into it any thing that defileth.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 27.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:40745:65"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Thou ſhalt be ſet free from all thy Luſts and Corruptions, for when thy Spirit ſhall be made perfect, not any Saint on Earth will be made partaker of the hundredth Part of that Inherent Grace, which the Soul of the meaneſt Saint ſhall be partaker of in Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Thou ſhalt be freed from the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of wicked and unreaſonable Men, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or there the weary are at rest.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 3. 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> All the Faculties of thy Soul ſhall be enlarged to the utmoſt Capacity, to know, love, enjoy, delight in and Praiſe thy Bleſſed God; <hi>When that which is perfect is come, then that which</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 10, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>is in Part ſhall be done away; for now we ſee through a Glaſs darkly, but then face to face: Now I know but in part, but then ſhall I know, as I alſo am known.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> That Sweet, Holy, Heavenly Work of Praiſing God, thou ſhalt be imployed in to all Eternity; and ſhalt perform it without the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 4. 8. to the end <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end. <hi>Rev.</hi> 15. 3, 4. <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.</note> leaſt laſſitude or wearineſs, nay, with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Delight and Complacency.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Thou ſhalt be cured of all thy Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and bodily Infirmities; there ſhall neither be aking Head, or aking Heart; there ſhall be nothing but Joy and Gladneſs, all Sorrow and Sighing ſhall fly away. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ninthly,</hi> Thy Vile Body ſhall be raiſed up at the laſt Day, <hi>and be made like Chriſt glorious Body.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 21.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tenthly</hi> and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> To conclude all, Thy Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhall be reunited to thy Soul, and they ſhall both together to all Eternity, enjoy ſo much Bliſs and Happineſs, as thou wilt ſay the one half (nay the one hundredth Part) was not told thee. <hi>For Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>hath entred into the Heart of Man the things that God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
